The crew's crossing gantry for ingress.
工作人员正通过塔台进入密封舱
Roger that.
收到
Inspired by the late President Kennedy...
在肯尼迪总统的启发之下…
in only seven years, America has risen to the challenge of what he called.
在仅仅7年内 美国已蓄势待发，挑战他所谓的…
"The most hazardous and dangerous and greatest adventure...
人类所面临最惊人、最危险…
"on which man has ever embarked."
“最伟大的冒险”
After trailing the Russians for years with our manned space program...
我们的载人太空计划在落后俄国数年之后…
and after that sudden and horrible fire...
并且在定期测试期间…
on the launch pad during a routine test...
发射台突然起了猛烈大火…
that killed American astronauts Gus Grissom...
使美国宇航员葛斯・格里森…
Ed White and Roger Chaffee...
艾德・怀特和罗杰・彻菲殉职之后…
there were serious doubts that we could beat the Russians to the moon.
一般人非常怀疑我们是否能够 比俄国人更早踏上月球
JULY 20, 1969 HOUSTON, TEXAS But tonight, a mere 18 months after the tragedy of Apollo 1...
1969年7月20日 ，德州休士顿 但今晚，距离阿波罗1号惨剧仅仅18个月…
the entire world watched in awe as Neil Armstrong and Buzz Aldrin...
全世界在敬畏之下看着 尼尔・阿姆斯特朗和波兹・阿尔德林…
landed on the moon.
登上月球
The big news came just a moment ago.
我们刚刚收到这条大新闻
Mission Control gave the spacecraft permission...
任务控制室允许太空船…
to go for the extravehicular activity...
走出飞行工具进行活动
that is, for the walk on the moon...
也就是说，在月球表面行走
far earlier than anticipated, 9.00 p.m. Eastern Daylight Time...
比预期时间要早得多 在东部日光时间晚间9点…
The important thing when you penetrate the lunar module is your attitude...
在穿透登月小艇时 最重要的就是你的位置…
and relative speed.
和相对速度
Let's say this is me here in the command module and this is you...
假设这是我在指挥小艇里 而这是你…
All right... in the LEM.
好 在登月小艇里
This thing sticking out here is called the probe.
伸出来的这根叫做探测器
Is that true? Absolutely.
真的吗？ 当然
Tracey, when you feel that thing slide in, everything's clicking...
崔西，当你感到那根滑入时 一切都很完美…
it's like no other feeling in the world.
全世界都找不到这么爽快的感觉
Some liquid propulsion. What's the occasion?
来点液态推进吧 这么热闹，干什么呀？
How's it going at Mission Control?
任务控制室的状况如何？
It's a nervous time. They're pacing around and smoking.
紧张时刻到了 他们抽着烟，来回踱步
Gene Kranz is gonna have puppies. Jim Lovell.
金・克兰兹会紧张死了 我是吉姆・勒维尔
This is Tracey.
她叫崔西
How do you do? This is the man.
幸会，崔西 就是他
Gemini 7. Gemini 12. Apollo 8. They were the first around the moon.
双子星7号、双子星12号、阿波罗8号 他们首先环绕月球
This guy did 10 laps.
绕了10圈
With one hand on the wheel. Make yourselves at home.
还只用一手握方向盘呢 你们要喝什么自己动手
This is the last champagne in the city of Houston.
这是休士顿市内的最后一瓶香槟
Very good. Everything else all right?
非常好 其他都没事吧？
Everything's on course. Okay. Cadet Lovell.
一切都上轨道了 看来不错，勒维尔学生
Hey, Dad. Put this on ice. Make sure it gets cold.
嘿，爸 把这个放在冰上，一定要让它够冷
You gonna get a haircut this week? I'm on vacation.
你这个礼拜要理发吗？ 我在放假耶
Get a haircut.
去理发啦
I wouldn't mind being up there tonight. God, who wouldn't.
真希望今晚是我在上面 谁不希望呢
Don't worry. Our day's coming.
别担心，很快会轮到我们的
They're not gonna cut the program before number 14.
他们不会在阿波罗14号之前取消计划的
You know, my cousin called.
你知道，我表弟打电话来
Asked who we bribed to get on Jim Lovell's crew.
问我们是向谁贿赂 才能被选入吉姆勒维尔的小组
I told him they wanted to make sure he got the best.
我告诉他，他们所选的人 必定是最优秀的
Well, they got that right.
他们的作法没错
What network do we want?
看哪一台？
Put on Walter!
华特！
Jules Bergman!
柏格曼！
John, turn it up!
约翰，开大声点！
I really appreciate...
很感谢…
you all coming to this dress rehearsal party for my Apollo 12 landing.
各位来此参加我的 阿波罗12号登陆彩排派对
Sit down, Conrad.
坐下，康拉德
I think we should all take a moment to recognize...
我觉得我们应该花点时间来表扬…
the exemplary...
阿姆斯特朗的候补人员…
hell, damn near heroic effort...
在这次历史性的月球漫步中…
displayed by Neil Armstrong's backup for this historic moon walk...
他和他的组员近乎英雄般的努力…
and, of course, his crew.
缔造出空前成果
Let's hear it for Jim Lovell, Ken Mattingly and Fred Haise.
让我们掌声鼓励吉姆・勒维尔 肯・马丁利还有佛列德・贺斯
There he is! Everybody quiet down!
他来了 ！大家小声点
Hey! Kids!
喂！孩子！
You got a good picture?
画面清楚吗？
We can verify the position of the opening I ought to have on the camera.
我们能核对摄影机上 应该出现的开口位置
You think it's too late for him to abort? He still has time to get out.
你觉得他放弃会不会太迟？ 他还有时间出去
He just needs somebody to wave him off. Pull up, Neil!
只要有人给个信号就行了 别登陆，尼尔！
Pull up!
往上飞！
Neil, we can see you coming down the ladder now.
尼尔，我们现在能看到你走下阶梯了
Look at those pictures.
你看看那画面
I'm at the foot of the ladder.
我就在那阶梯底下
The LEM footpads are only depressed in the surface about...
登月小艇的底阶 只在月球表面陷下了约…
one or two inches.
3至4公分
It's almost like a powder.
简直像粉一样
Armstrong is on the moon.
阿姆斯特朗登陆月球 阿姆斯特朗登陆月球了
Neil Armstrong, 38-year-old American...
尼尔・阿姆斯特朗，38岁的美国人
standing on the surface of the moon...
在1969年7月20日…
on this July 20, 1969.
站立在月球表面
That's one small step for man...
这是个人的一小步…
one giant leap for mankind.
却是全人类的一大步
His quote was.
他说…
"That's one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind."
“这是个人的一小步 却是全人类的一大步”
You're drunk, Lovell.
你醉了，勒维尔
I'm not used to the champagne.
我不习惯喝香槟
Me, neither.
我也是
I can't deal with cleaning up. Let's sell the house.
清理房子我最受不了 不如把房子卖了吧
All right, let's sell the house.
好，我们把房子卖了
They're back inside now looking up at us.
他们现在已回到船上，看着我们
Isn't that something?
真了不起
I bet Jannie Armstrong doesn't get a wink of sleep tonight.
我敢说珍妮・阿姆斯特朗今晚 一定不敢合眼
When you were on the far side on 8, I didn't sleep at all.
你在阿波罗8号上到了月球另一边时 我也没法睡觉
I just vacuumed over and over again.
我只是拿着吸尘器不停地吸
Christopher Columbus, Charles Lindbergh, and Neil Armstrong.
哥伦布、林伯格，现在又加上阿姆斯特朗
Neil Armstrong.
尼尔・阿姆斯特朗
From now on, we live in a world where man has walked on the moon.
从现在起，我们这个世界 已经有人在月球上漫步过了
It's not a miracle.
这不是奇迹
We just decided to go.
我们只是有这个决心
On Apollo 8, we were so close...
在阿波罗8号上，我们靠得非常近
just 60 nautical miles down and...
只距离下方110公里
It was as if I could just...
简直像是能…
step out and walk on the face of it.
踏出去，在地面上走
I want to go back there.
我想再回去
Where's my mountain?
我的山在哪里？
It's right up by the...
就在上面的…
Do you see where the shadow crosses...
你看到阴影穿过…
the white area there? That's the Sea of Tranquility...
白色区域的地方吗？ 那是宁静海
and your mountain's on the edge of that.
你的山就在那个边缘
It's your mountain, Marilyn. Mount Marilyn.
那就是你的山，玛丽莲，玛丽莲山
I don't see it.
我看不到
Well, you gotta look harder.
你要仔细看
You look harder...
你一面仔细看…
while I...
我一面…
Vehicle Assembly Building Cape Kennedy, Florida
交通工具组装大楼 佛州肯尼迪角
The astronaut is the most visible member of a very large team.
宇航员是一个非常庞大的团队中 最引人注目的人员
OCTOBER 30, 1969
1969年10月30日
All of us, down to the guy sweeping the floor...
我们所有人 下至扫地的清洁人员
are honored to be a part of it.
都非常荣幸能参与
What did the man say? "Give me a lever long enough and I'll move the world"?
古人是怎么说的？ “给我一根够长的杠杆，我就能移动世界” ？
That's what we're doing here. This is divine inspiration, folks.
我们现在就是这样 各位，这是圣者的启发
It's the best part of each one of us, the belief that anything is possible.
这是我们每个人最优秀之处 相信自己什么都做得到
Things like a computer that can fit into a single room...
就像创造出比一个房间更小的电脑…
and hold millions of pieces of information...
储存几百万条信息
or the Saturn 5 rocket.
或是土星5号火箭
This is the actual launch vehicle that will be taking Alan Shepard...
艾伦薛波德和他的人员…
and his crew on the first leg of the Apollo 13 mission.
就是要乘坐这座发射工具 进行阿波罗13号任务的第一部份
When are you going up again, Jim?
你什么时候要再上去，吉姆？
I'm slated to be the commander of Apollo 14 sometime late next year.
我预计将在明年底 担任阿波罗14号的指挥官
If there is an Apollo 14.
如果有阿波罗14号的话
People in my state have been asking why we're continuing...
我们州的人民一直在问 既然已经比俄国人更早上月球了…
to fund this program now that we've beaten the Russians to the moon.
为什么还要资助这个计划？
Imagine if Christopher Columbus had come back from the New World...
只要想如果哥伦布从新大陆回来…
and no one returned in his footsteps.
却没有人跟随他的脚步会怎样
Attention, all personnel. Clear level 3.
请注意，所有人员离开第3层
Are there any other questions?
有其它问题吗？
How do you go to the bathroom in space?
在太空中如何上厕所？
It's a highly technical process...
这个过程需要非常高超的技术…
of cranking down the window and looking for a gas station which...
把窗户摇下来，找加油站…
There's Deke Slayton.
迪克・史雷顿来了
You might be able to answer this lady's question.
你也许能回答这位女士的问题
Deke is one of the original Mercury 7 astronauts, ladies and gentlemen.
各位，迪克是水星7号最早的宇航员
Now he's our boss. He hands out the astronauts' flight assignments...
现在他是我们的老板 他分配宇航员飞行任务
so naturally we kick back part of our salaries to Deke.
所以，我们当然每月 把部份薪水回扣给迪克
How much this month? Can I have a minute? Something's come up.
这个月要多少？ 我跟你单独谈一下好吗？ 有点事
Sure.
当然
Hey!
嘿！
Anybody home? I'm not being a cheerleader, Mom!
有人在家吗？ 我不要扮啦啦队员，妈！
You don't understand! I worked so hard!
你不懂啦！我很用心耶！
Maybe I don't understand...
也许我不懂！
but you are not wearing that out in this neighborhood.
但你不准在这附近穿那件服装
She's not even wearing a bra! You can see everything!
她连胸罩也不穿！ 都被人看光了 ！
Shut up!
闭嘴！
Hey, everybody. Marilyn, trick or treat.
嘿，孩子们，玛丽莲 万圣节愉快
You know that Easter vacation trip we had planned for Acapulco?
我们复活节不是计划 到阿卡波可去玩吗？
I was thinking there might be a slight change in destination.
我想可能要改变一下目的地了
Really?
真的
Maybe, say...
也许，去…
the moon.
月球
Al Shepard's ear infection has flared up...
薛波德的耳朵发炎越来越严重
and we've all been bumped up to the prime crew of Apollo 13.
我们都被提前征召 成为阿波罗13号的主要队员
Straight to the head of the line and the Fra Mauro Highlands.
直接前往第一线和佛拉莫洛高地
Six months? You're moving up six months?
6个月 ？ 你要提前6个月 ？
Dad, can I please wear this?
爸，我穿这件好不好？
Sure.
好
No! Absolutely not.
不行！绝对不行
They're not rushing things, are they? You'll be ready in six months?
他们会不会太赶了？ 你六个月能准备得好吗？
We'll be ready. I wouldn't want to be around Al Shepard tonight.
我们会准备好的 我今晚可不想跟宇航员一起混
I gotta get over there and get up to speed on this.
我要到那里去 赶快做充份准备
Go.
去啊
I'm gonna walk on the moon, Marilyn.
我就要在月球上漫步了，玛丽莲
I know. I can't believe it.
我知道，真不敢相信
Naturally, it's 13. Why 13?
偏偏是13，为什么就偏是13？
It comes after 12, hon.
因为它在12之后
Apollo 13, you are go for pyro arm and docking.
阿波罗13号，你要进行 爆破设定和小艇对接
All systems are nominal and on the line.
系统正常，符合理想状况
MANNED SPACECRAFT CENTER HOUSTON, TEXAS S-4B is stable, SLA panels are drifting free.
载人太空船中心 德州休士顿 土星4B稳定 登月小艇连接器翼板能自由漂浮
3 MONTHS PRIOR TO LAUNCH The drogue is clear. The docking target is clear.
发射前3个月 锥形管已脱离 连接目标已脱离
I'm coming up on that now. Two, one, mark.
我要接近了 二、一、成功
Seventy-five feet. We're coming up on docking.
23公尺 我们即将连接了
Let's shut down some thrusters on them. Let's see what he does.
我们把推进器关掉一点 看看他会怎样
Wait a minute.
等等
I lost something here. I can't translate up.
有点不灵，无法移动太空船
Houston, we are drifting down and away.
休士顿，我们向下漂走了
Wanna back off and take another run? No, I got it.
要不要回头再试一次？ 不用，我来
Let me just try and get it stable here.
我试试看能不能稳定下来
I'm gonna reset the high gain. I've got the target back in the reticle.
我要重新设定维修艇主天线 我在标线上找回目标了
Okay, we're stable. Recycle the valves.
好，我们稳下了，再循环一次阀门
Forty feet. They're all gray.
开 关 12公尺 都呈灰色
Twenty.
6公尺
Ten feet.
3公尺
Capture. That's it!
命中 好！
That's it. Sweet move, Ken. Beautiful.
棒！ 真准，肯，干得好
Gentlemen, that is the way we do that. Man, that woke me up.
各位，我们就是要这样做 真是，我总算搞清楚了
Apollo 13 backup crew, you're up in the simulator.
阿波罗13号候补人员 换你们上模拟机
Nice job, gentlemen. That's three hours of boredom...
大家干得好 无聊了3个小时…
followed by seven seconds of sheer terror.
最后7秒却吓死人
Good job, guys. You just won the Christmas turkey.
大家辛苦了 你们圣诞节有火鸡可吃了
Nice try, Frank.
厉害，法兰克
You really outfoxed them.
你实在比他们强
Yeah, but it wasn't perfect. Used up too much fuel.
是啊，可是还不完美 用的燃料太多
You're above the curve.
你还在曲线标准之内
Not by much. Listen, guys, I wanna work it again.
只差一点而已 各位，我想再练习一次
We gotta be up with the dawn patrol headed for Bethpage at 0700.
我们要拂晓出巡 早上7点到贝斯佩吉去
Wheels up at 0700. Yeah, I know...
早上7点出发 我知道…
but my rate of turn is still a little slow there.
但我回头的速度还是有点慢
I really think we should work it again.
我真的觉得我们应该再练习一次
Let's get it right. Set it up again, Frank.
我们把它做好 再设定一次，法兰克
Okay, 13 backup crew. It'll have to wait.
好，13号候补人员请稍候
Prime crew's up for another run.
主要人员要再练习一次
Apollo 13, we show S-4B shutdown...
阿波罗13号，我们显示 土星4B已停机
and all systems are nominal.
所有系统正常
Fred, set the S-band omni to B...
佛列德，把S频全向天线设到B
and when you get in the LEM, to forward.
进入登月小艇后，设定为前方天线
Good shape over here.
这里状况良好
Hey, we got a problem.
我们有问题了
Cabin depress. Repeat, cabin depress.
机舱减压，重覆，机舱减压
Ken, get your helmet on! I can't get it locked!
肯，戴上头盔！ 锁不起来！
Houston, something ripped a big hole in us! We got rapid depress!
休士顿，有东西把我们戳了个大洞！ 我们气压急速下降
Oh, God!
天哪！
I thought the stars would fall on you.
我以为星星会掉下来
MARCH 23, 19703 WEEKS PRIOR TO LAUNCH
1970年3月23日 发射前3星期
That's silly. Stars can't fall on us.
真笨，星星才不会掉下来
You're a smarter kid than I was.
你比我小时候聪明
How long will it take you to get to the moon?
到月球要多久时间？
Four days.
4天
But that's pretty fast.
但很快
See, this is the Saturn 4B booster...
你看，这是土星4B推进器
and it shoots us away from the Earth...
它把我们从地球上射出去
as fast as a bullet from a gun...
像子弹从枪里射出去一样快
until the moon's gravity actually grabs us and pulls us...
直到月球的引力能把我们向它吸去
into a circle around the moon...
绕着月球转
which is called an orbit. All right?
那叫做轨道，对不对？
Fred and I float down the tunnel into the lunar module...
佛列德跟我漂下隧道 进入登月小艇
this spidery-Iooking guy.
这小艇看起来很像蜘蛛
Only holds two people, and it's just for landing on the moon.
只能坐两个人，用来登上月球
And I take the controls, steer it around...
我接手控制，掌握方向
and I fly it down...
我把它往下飞
adjusting it here, the attitude there, pitch, roll...
调一下这里，调一下那里位置 上下、左右移动…
for a nice, soft landing on the moon.
然后稳稳地登陆在月球上
Better than Neil Armstrong. Way better than Pete Conrad.
比阿姆斯特朗还行 比康拉德还厉害
Did you know the astronauts in the fire?
你认识被烧死的宇航员吗？
Yeah. I knew the astronauts in the fire. All of them.
对，我认识那些烧死的宇航员 都认识
Could that happen again?
那事会不会再发生？
Well, I'll tell you something about that fire.
我来告诉你那场火的事
A lot of things went wrong.
许多事情出问题
The door.
门
It's called the hatch. They couldn't get it open when they needed to get out.
这叫做闸门，他们无法打开这道门 结果出不去
That was one thing.
这是其一
A lot of things went wrong in that fire.
那场火中许多事情出问题
Did they fix it?
他们有没有修好？
Yes, absolutely. We fixed it.
当然，我们修好了
It's not a problem anymore.
已经不成问题了
I can't believe they still have you doing public appearances.
我真不敢相信他们还叫你 到公众场合露面
Well, Henry Hurt was all over me.
亨利・贺特一直来缠我
With a training schedule this tight, they shouldn't be asking.
训练进度这么紧，他们不应该来找你
It's the program, Marilyn. You know, it's NASA.
这在计划内，玛丽莲 国家航太总署就是这样
Hey, you're Jim Lovell, aren't you?
嘿，你不是吉姆勒维尔吗？
Hey! Lucky 13!
嘿，十三大吉！
Right on!
加油！
That's the second time it's done that.
这已经是第二次熄火了
I was looking at the kids' school schedule coming up.
我在看孩子接下来的学校进度
It's a very busy week.
下礼拜很忙
I'm thinking about not going to the launch.
我想不去看火箭发射了
The kids need me at home.
孩子需要我在家陪
Marilyn, we've had these kids for a while now.
玛丽莲，我们带孩子已经有一阵子了
They've never kept you from coming to the other launches.
你从未因为他们 而错过其他的火箭发射
But your mother just had this stroke.
但你妈刚刚中风
Mom's fine.
妈没事的
It's not like I've never been to a launch.
我又不是没看过火箭发射
The other wives have not done three.
其他人的太太都没有看过三次
I just don't think I can go through all that.
我只是觉得无法承受压力
I'll just be glad when this one's over.
这次能平安结束，我就很满意了
You're gonna miss a hell of a show.
你会错过一次很棒的盛会
Hey, guys. See you in a few weeks.
嘿，各位，过几个礼拜见
Take care. Bring us back a moon rock.
保重，带一块月球岩石回来给我们
The number 13 doesn't bother you? Only if it's a Friday.
你不觉得13号不吉利？ 只要不是星期五就好
APRIL 7, 1970 CAPE KENNEDY, FLORIDA 4 DAYS PRIOR TO LAUNCH
1970年4月7日，佛州肯尼迪角 发射前4日
Apollo 13, lifting off at 1300 hours and 13 minutes...
阿波罗13号 将在13点13分升空
and entering the moon's gravity on April 13?
然后在4月13号进入月球引力范围？
Ken Mattingly here has been doing some scientific experiments...
针对这个现象，这位肯马丁利…
regarding that very phenomenon.
做过一些科学实验
Yes, well, I had a black cat...
对，我让一只黑猫…
walk over a broken mirror...
在登月小艇阶梯之下…
under the lunar module ladder. It didn't seem to be a problem.
走在破的镜子上，似乎没有问题
We're considering a letter we got...
我们接获一封信，说我们…
which said we ought to take a pig with us for good luck.
应该带只猪一起去，以求吉利 我们会考虑的
Does it bother you that the public thinks this is routine?
大众把这次飞行视为例行任务 你会不会觉得不高兴？
There's nothing routine about flying to the moon. I can vouch for that.
飞到月球去决不是例行任务 这点我可以保证
I think that an astronaut's last mission...
我想一位宇航员的最后一次任务…
his final flight is always very special.
最后一次飞行，总是非常特殊的
Why is this your last, Jim?
为什么是你的最后一次，吉姆？
I'm in command of the best ship...
我带领着一艘最优秀的太空船…
with the best crew that anybody could ask for...
以及人人称羡的最优秀人员…
and I'll be walking in a place where there's 400 degrees difference...
我将踏足的地方 日夜温差将有…
between sunlight and shadow.
摄氏222度
I can't imagine ever topping that.
我想没什么能比这种体验更美妙了
APRIL 9, 19702 DAYS PRIOR TO LAUNCH
1970年4月9日 发射前2日
We have that scheduled for 0900 hours tomorrow.
预定明天上午9点进行
That's not gonna work, Walter. Why?
这样不行，华特 为什么？
Freddo and I are going over the lunar surface experiments tomorrow...
明天佛列德跟我要练习 月球表面的实验
and Ken's gonna be back in the simulator. We're going over the flight plan tonight.
肯要回去做模拟机 我们今晚要练习航行计划
Gonna pay a visit to this machine after you're hard down.
我待会儿再来看这机器
Jim, we've got a problem.
吉姆，我们有点麻烦
We just got some blood work from the lab. Charlie Duke has the measles.
我们刚从检验室得到抽血报告 查理杜克得了麻疹
So we need a new backup.
所以我们需要新的候补人员
You've all been exposed to it. I've had the measles.
你们都可能受到感染 我得过麻疹了
Ken Mattingly hasn't.
肯马丁利还没得过
You wanna break up my crew two days before the launch...
现在我们已经驾轻就熟 彼此默契十足
when we can predict each other's moves, read the tone of each other's voices?
你却要在发射两天前 把我的小组换人？
Ken Mattingly will get seriously ill...
肯马丁利严重发病的时候…
precisely when you and Haise will be ascending from the lunar surface.
你和贺斯正好要从月球表面上来
That's a lousy time for a fever.
这时候发烧可不妙
Jack Swigert has been out of the loop for weeks.
杰克史威格好几个礼拜没练习了 技巧很生疏
He's fully qualified to fly this mission.
他有充份资格出这次任务
He's a fine pilot, but when was the last time he was in a simulator?
他的驾驶技巧熟练，可是 他上次进模拟机是什么时候？
I'm sorry, Jim. I understand how you feel.
很抱歉，吉姆，我了解你的感受
We can do one of two things.
现在只有两条路
We can either scrub Mattingly and go with Swigert...
让史威格代替马丁利上阵…
or we can bump all three of you to a later mission.
不然就要把你们3个都换下来 等下一次任务再说
I've trained for the Fra Mauro Highlands...
我为了佛拉・莫洛高地而苦苦受训
and this is flight surgeon horseshit, Deke!
这个医官却在这里放狗屁，迪克！
Jim, if you hold out for Ken, you will not be on Apollo 13.
吉姆，如果你要跟肯一起出任务 就不能上阿波罗13号
It's your decision.
你自己决定
Let it ring.
别接吧
Listen, I gotta take that.
这通电话一定要接
Why? Because I'm on the backup crew...
为什么？ 因为我是候补人员
and the backup crew has to set up the guest list and book the hotel rooms.
候补人员必须准备来宝名册 订酒店房间
Yes, sir.
是的，长官
I understand.
我了解
Thank you, sir.
谢谢，长官
Damn.
妈的
Medical guys.
医官
I had a feeling when they started doing all the blood tests that...
他们一开始验血，我就觉得…
I mean, I know it's their ass if I get sick up there, but, I mean... Jesus!
我知道，如果我在太空中生病 那就是他们的责任，可是这，靠！
Swigert, he'll be fine.
史威格，他不错的
He's strong.
他身体好
It'll be a hell of a mission. One for the books.
这将是一次漂亮的任务 会名留青史
You sure about this? Why don't I talk to Deke?
你确定吗？ 怎么不让我跟迪克说？
I'm sure we can work this out.
我们一定能把事搞定
This was my call.
这是我的决定
Must've been a tough one.
你一定下了很大决心
Look, I don't have the measles.
我没有麻疹
I'm not gonna get the measles.
我不会得麻疹
Ken, wait up.
肯，等等
Trajectory is holding steady. We're right on the line.
曲线稳定，我们正在轨道上
We're into program 64 at 0.05 G...
我们进入64程序，引力0. 05
so we're feeling that gravity now.
所以现在感到引力了
Houston, we are at 400,000 feet passing entry interface.
休士顿，我们高度12万2千公尺 正通过进入大气层的介点
About to lose signal.
即将失去信号
Re-entry data is nominal, and we have radio blackout.
重新进入的数据正常 我们无线电暂时不灵
What's the story here?
怎么回事？
I got a corridor light. We're coming in too shallow.
我看到狭长灯亮起 我们进来得太缓了
I'm going to manual.
我用手控
Houston, switching to SCS. Roger, 13.
休士顿，换成稳控系统 收到，13号
Okay, we're at three Gs.
好，气压是三Ｇ
Five Gs.
五Ｇ
We're coming in too steep.
现在太陡了
I'm gonna stay in this roll and see if I can pull us out.
我要继续滚动 看能不能减速
We're at eight Gs.
现在八Ｇ了
Nine.
九Ｇ
Ten.
十Ｇ
We're at 12 Gs. 12 Gs. We're burning up.
我们达到十二Ｇ了 十二Ｇ，要烧起来了
Damn it!
妈的！
I gave them a false indicator light at entry interface.
我在他们进入大气层时 给了一个错误的指示灯
Even Mattingly didn't get it the first time.
连马丁利第一次都看不出来
How are you feeling, Freddo?
你觉得如何，佛列德？
Charbroiled.
烤焦了
What happened?
怎么回事？
Came in too steep. We're dead.
进来时太陡了，惨死
No shit.
废话
We were into program 67 there.
我们进入67程序了
We're gonna do this again, obviously.
显然要再来一次
Give us a minute to get our switches reset.
等我们一下，重新设定切换钮
Jim, could we have a word?
吉姆，我跟你谈谈好吗？
Sure, Deke.
好，迪克
We're going to drop offline and debrief this one on our own.
这次我们不要上线 自己来会报
If I had a dollar every time they killed me in this thing...
如果我每次死在这里 都会得到1块钱…
I wouldn't have to work for you, Deke.
那我就不用来为你上班了，迪克
Well, we have two days. We'll be ready.
我们还有两天，会准备好的
Let's do it again.
再来一次吧
Do it again.
再来一次
Get down, Fred! Stephen, come here!
下来，佛列德！史蒂芬，过来！
April 10, 1970 Night Before Launch
1970年4月10日 发射前夜
We can't go across that road.
不能越过那条路
We don't want Daddy to get our germs and get sick in outer space.
可不要让爸爸碰到我们的细菌 在外太空生病
Hey, boys. Not giving your mom a hard time, are you?
嘿，孩子，没有给妈妈惹麻烦吧？
Princess, you look beautiful.
小公主，你看起来好美
That looks like Marilyn Lovell.
那看起来好像是玛丽莲・勒维尔
But it can't be. She's not coming to the launch.
但是不可能 她是不会来看火箭发射的
I heard it was gonna be a hell of a show.
我听说到时会很壮观
Who told you that?
谁说的？
Some guy I know.
一个男的
You can't live without me.
你没有我活不下去
Okay, folks. Let's say good night.
好，各位，说晚安吧
It's a big day tomorrow for the guys. Good night!
明天将是这些人的大日子 晚安！
You hear about Ken?
你听说肯的事了吗？
Yeah.
有
April 11, 1970 Cape Kennedy, Florida
1970年4月11日 佛州肯尼迪角
Stand back, please.
请退后
Guenter Wendt!
宫特・温特！
I wonder where Guenter went?
不知道宫特去哪里了？
You walk on the moon, ja? Ja, we walk...
你要在月球漫步，对？ 对，我们要在月球上…
and we talk on the moon.
一面走、 一面说
How do you feel? Pretty good?
你觉得怎样？ 还不错吧？
Might be a little warmer in here.
这里好像比较热一点
How are you? Good.
今天好吗？ 好
Ready? Yeah.
准备好了吗？ 好了
God, no.
唉呀
Oxygen purge system. Check.
好，氧气检查系统 备齐
Helmet restraint ring. Check.
头盔控制环
Communication umbilical on.
通讯补给线接上
Fred. What?
佛列德 什么？
Gum. Sorry.
口香糖 抱歉
Thanks.
谢谢
I'm gonna give these guys a beautiful ride.
我会让他们一路顺畅
I'm sure you will, Jack.
你会的，杰克
You need more air?
需要多点空气吗？
You want some apple?
要不要吃苹果？
I hate this already.
我已经开始担心了
You're not just about to pop, are you?
你该不会快生了吧？
No. I got 30 days till this blasts off.
不会，离预产期还有30天
MISSION CONTROL HOUSTON, TEXAS
德州休士顿任务控制室
This is for Gene.
这个拿给金恩
Mrs. Kranz has pulled out the needle and thread again.
克兰兹太太又在秀她的针线活儿了
The last one looked like he bought it off a gypsy.
上一件好像是他跟吉普赛人买的
Well, you can't argue with tradition.
传统总是不能违背的
Copy that.
收到
This is from your wife, Gene.
金恩，这是你太太给你的
Thank you, Tom.
谢谢，汤姆
I was starting to get worried.
我还在担心呢
There we go.
来
I like that one. Sharp.
这件漂亮，金恩 帅，金恩
Jim, you're all set.
吉姆，你准备好了
Very sharp.
真帅
Gene, I guess we can go now.
金恩，我们应该能走了
Save it for splashdown, guys.
等到安全着陆再鼓掌吧
Apollo 13 flight controllers, listen up.
阿波罗13号飞行控制员，请听好
Give me a "go, no go" for launch.
告诉我你们是否已准备好发射
Booster. Go.
推进器系统工程师 好
RETRO. Go.
返航控制员
FIDO. We're go, Flight.
飞航动态控制员 好，主任
Guidance. Go.
导航控制员 好
Surgeon. Go, Flight.
医生 好，主任
EECOM.
电子与环境指令台
We're go, Flight. GNC.
导航与领航控制员
TELMU. Go.
遥测电子与舱外活动 好
Control. Go.
控制员
Procedures. INCO. Go.
程序，仪器通讯控制员 好
FAO. We are go.
飞行活动与实验控制员 都好
Network. Recovery. Go.
纲路，修复 好
CAPCOM. We're go, Flight.
机舱通讯员 我们好了，主任
Launch control, this is Houston. We are go for launch.
发射控制室，这是休士顿 我们准备好发射了
Roger that, Houston.
收到，休士顿
Launch Control Center Cape Kennedy, Florida
发射控制中心 佛州肯尼迪角
Pad leader, what's your status?
发射台主任，状况如何？
We are go for launch.
我们准备好了
T minus 60 seconds and counting.
倒数60秒发射
Stand by. Roger.
预备 收到
Fuel pumps.
燃料帮浦
This is it. A few bumps and we're hauling the mail.
来罗，再过几关 我们就准备送信到外太空去喽
Control, this is Guidance. We're ready for takeoff.
控制室，这是导航室 我们准备发射了
We are go for launch.
准备发射
T minus...
倒数…
fifteen, fourteen...
十五、 十四…
thirteen, twelve, eleven...
十三、 十二、 十一…
ten, nine...
十、 九…
eight, seven...
八、 七…
six.
六
Ignition sequence starts.
点火序列开始
Three, two, one.
三、 二、 一
Ignition!
点火！
The clock is running!
启动了 ！
We have lift-off!
我们离地了 ！
LAUNCH Houston, we have cleared the tower at 13.13.
休士顿，我们在13点13分离开塔台
Okay, guys, we got it.
好，各位，成功了
Come on, baby.
来吧
Altitude is on the line.
位置正常
Velocity right on the line.
速率正常
Roll complete. We are pitching.
旋转完毕，准备偏航
13, stand by for Mode One Bravo.
13号，准备进入第一模式
FIDO, how we looking?
飞航动态控制员，情况如何？
Looks good, Flight. Right down the middle.
看来不错，主任，正如预期
We see your BPC is clear, 13.
我们看到你的推进保护套 已经脱离了，13号
Roger. EDS to manual.
收到，紧急检测系统转为手控
Inboard.
舱内
Get ready for a little jolt, fellas.
各位，会有点颠簸
That was some little jolt.
还真是只有一点
Tower jett.
塔台已丢弃
Houston, we've got a center engine cut-off. Go on the other four.
休士顿，我们中央引擎已停机 用另外四个
Roger that, 13. We show the same.
收到，13号，我们这里显示相同
Booster, can you confirm that cut-off?
推进器，能不能证实已停机？
Roger. Looks like we lost it. FIDO, what'll that do to us?
收到，好像已经不行 飞航动态控制员，那会怎样？
Stand by, Flight.
准备好，主任
I need to know if the IUs are correcting for the number five shutdown.
我必须知道惯性机件是否因为 第五引擎停机而加以修正
Houston, what's the story on engine five?
休士顿，第五引擎如何？
We're still go. We'll be all right as long as we don't lose another one.
没问题 只要其它引擎不再停机就没事
Roger that. We're not sure why the inboard was out...
收到 我们不确定舱内引擎为什么失灵…
but the other engines are go, so we're gonna burn those engines...
但其它引擎都没事 所以就让那些引擎…
a little bit longer.
再多用一会儿吧
Roger that. Our gimbals are good.
收到，平衡环状况良好
Our trim is good.
位势良好
Looks like we just had our glitch for this mission.
在这以后应该不会再有问题了
13, stand by for staging. Roger that.
13号，准备将燃料箱分离 收到
S-2 shutdown. S-4B ignition.
土星2停机，土星4B点火
Thrust looks good, Flight.
推进情况不错，主任
Flight, S-4B cut-off in 10 seconds.
主任，土星4B十秒后停机
13, this is Houston. Predicted cut-off is 12 plus 34, over.
13号，这里是休士顿 预计12分34秒后停机，完毕
Coming up on 12 minutes, 34.
等12分34秒
And...
然后…
SECO!
主级引擎停机！
Shutdown.
停用
And that, gentlemen, is how we do that.
各位，我们就这样做到了
Oh, boy. Hope I can sleep.
天哪，希望我睡得着
Mom, that was loud.
妈，好吵啊
Here, hold my hand.
来，抓住我的手
I can't believe you did this four times.
我不敢相信你来看了四次
The worst part's over.
最可怕的时刻已经过了
It is?
是吗？
Listen, this doesn't stop for me until he lands on that aircraft carrier.
直到他在那航空母舰上着陆为止 我一直会担心
Well, you just look so calm about it.
你看起来倒是很冷静
If the flight surgeon had to okay me for this mission, I'd be grounded.
如果我要通过医官检验才能 来看这次任务的话，我准出不了门
Mrs. Haise! Can we speak to you?
勒维尔太太！贺斯太太！ 能不能和你们说句话？
Remember, you're proud, happy, and thrilled.
记住，你要表现得骄傲、 快乐、 高兴
How're you feeling? Very proud...
你感觉如何？ 非常骄傲…
and very happy, and we're thrilled.
非常快乐，也很高兴
Flight, Booster. I show S-4B shutdown.
主任，推进器，我这里显示 土星4B已停机
TLI is on the money. Looks good, Flight.
超月球射入轨道准确无误 情况良好，主任
Roger, FIDO.
收到，飞航动态控制员
We're going to the moon!
我们要登上月球了 ！
We have reacquisition of signal at Hawaii.
主任，我们在夏威夷重新获得信号
Flight, everything looks good.
主任，一切良好
Okay, Houston. CMP here.
好，休士顿，这里是指挥小艇机长
I've exchanged couches with Jim. I'm in the pilot's seat.
我跟吉姆换了位置 现在我在驾驶座上
I'm gonna go ahead and get set for transposition and docking.
我要开始准备布署并连接 登月小艇和指挥小艇
Roger that, Jack.
收到，杰克
Freddo, you okay?
佛列德，你没事吧？
Everybody, let's get turned around and pick up the lunar module.
各位，我们回头去接登月小艇
Odyssey, you're go for pyro arm and docking...
奥德赛指挥小艇，你准备好 爆破设定和小艇对接
and we recommend you secure cabin pressurization.
我们建议你维持座舱气压
Roger that.
收到
Okay, we're ready for CSM separation.
好，我们准备将指挥与维修小艇脱离
Okay, SMRCS isol valves are all gray.
好，维修小艇反应控制系统 隔离阀都呈灰色
Okay, Swigert, command module pilot.
好，史威格，指挥小艇机长
She's all yours.
现在全权归你指挥了
Houston, we've got a good separation.
休士顿，我们顺利分离了
The S-4B is stable. Translation looks good.
土星4B状况稳定 平移看来良好
Reconfirm then, 13. We're gonna start to pitch around...
请再次确认，13号 我们要开始偏航…
to line up with the LEM.
以对准登月小艇
You know, Freddo, Frank Borman...
佛列德，你知道吗，法兰克・波曼…
was upchucking most of the way to the moon on Apollo 8.
坐阿波罗8号上月球时 是一路吐过去的
I'm all right. I just ate too much breakfast. Let's go to work.
我还好，只是早餐吃多了点 我们开始工作吧
And pitching up.
向上偏航
Pitch rate, 2.5 degrees per second.
偏率每秒2. 5度
Roger, Jack.
收到，杰克
We see you pitching around.
我们看到你在偏向了
Keep an eye on that telemetry.
注意遥测
Roger that. If Swigert can't dock this thing, we don't have a mission.
收到，如果史威格不能把 这两座小艇对接，这次任务就失败了
How's the alignment? GDC align.
对准情况如何？ 陀螺显示连接器对准
Thrusting forward.
向前推进
One hundred feet.
30公尺
Watch the alignment now.
现在注意对准
Don't worry, guys.
各位别担心
I'm on top of it.
我控制住了
FIDO, let me know when you're ready.
飞航动态控制员，准备好了告诉我
Let's uplink that.
用通讯频道来传输
How we looking? We're not there yet. Forty feet.
看来如何？ 还没到，12公尺
Twenty.
6公尺
Come on, rookie, park that thing.
来吧，菜鸟，接上吧
Ten feet.
3公尺
Capture.
成功
That's it.
好了
Talk back is barber pole. Go ahead and retract.
指示灯已关闭 开始撤回
Houston, we have hard dock.
休士顿，我们对接成功
Roger, we understand. That's a good deal, Jack.
收到，了解了 干得好，杰克
Let's start back up with procedure 17.
开始以17号程序退后
Houston, we have LEM extraction.
休士顿，我们登月小艇抽出
We copy that, 13.
信号收到，13号
Now you're off to the Fra Mauro Highlands.
现在你们要前往佛拉莫洛高地了
I gotta get out of this suit. Houston, we are ready...
我要把这上衣脱下来 休士顿，我们准备好…
for the beginning of the PTC...
开始进入消极式热控位置
and I think once we're in that barbecue roll, Jack and I will eat.
我们一进入该位置 杰克和我就要吃东西了
Hey, I'm hungry. Are you sure?
嘿，我饿了 真的？
I could eat the ass out of a dead rhinoceros.
我连犀牛屁股都肯吃
We got a smooth one? By the numbers so far.
这次任务顺利吗？ 依照数据显示，没错
We just ran a minimum load test on the cooling system...
我们刚对冷却系统 执行了最低载荷测试
See you tomorrow. Take care.
明天见 保重
DAY 3 APRIL 13
第3天，4月13日
It's too bad we can't demonstrate this on TV.
可惜我们无法在电视上示范这招
What a shame.
可惜啊
Overboard dump coming up.
向舱外排出了
Here it comes...
来罗
the constellation Urion.
金尿星座
Now, that's a beautiful sight.
真好看
Barbara, we are going to your father's broadcast.
芭芭拉，我们要去看你爸的转播
No! I'm never coming out!
不要，我不要出门 ！
I hate Paul! No one else can ever play their records again!
我恨保罗！ 谁也别想再放他们的唱片了 ！
She's still going on about the stupid Beatles breaking up?
她还因为那个笨蛋披头四解散 在大发神经啊？
They're not stupid! You're stupid!
他们不是笨蛋！ 你才是！
I know you're mourning.
我知道你很难过
I'm not going, Mom! Dad won't know if we're there!
我不要去，妈！ 我们不去爸也不会知道！
The whole world is going to be watching this broadcast, and so are we.
全世界的人都要去看转播 我们也要去
Good evening, America...
晚安，美国
and welcome aboard Apollo 13.
欢迎登上阿波罗13号
I'm Jim Lovell, and we're broadcasting to you tonight...
我是吉姆勒维尔 我们今晚向各位转播的所在地…
from an altitude of almost 200,000 miles...
是远离地球表面…
away from the face of the Earth...
高度将近32万公里之处
and we have a pretty good show in store for you tonight.
今晚节目非常精彩
We are going to show you just what...
我们即将让各位看到…
life is like for the three of us here...
我们三个人在这…
in the vast expanse of outer space.
宽广无际的外太空中的生活
One of the first things we'd like to do...
我们首先要…
is provide you with the appropriate background music.
向各位提供适当的背景音乐
So, hit it there, Freddo.
开始吧，佛列德
That was supposed to be the theme to 2001...
本来应该放 “2001年太空漫游” 的主题曲…
in honor of our command module, Odyssey.
以表扬我们的指挥小艇奥得赛号
There seems to have been a last-minute change in the program.
但在最后一刻节目似乎有所变动
When I go up on 19, I'm gonna take my entire collection of Johnny Cash along.
我如果上了阿波罗19号 我要把强尼卡许的所有歌都带上去
Hey, Marilyn. Where's their broadcast?
嘿，玛丽莲 他们的转播在哪里？
All the networks dumped us.
所有电视公司都不播了
One said we made going to the moon...
有一家说我们登陆月球的节目…
as exciting as a trip to Pittsburgh.
跟去工业城玩一样无聊
My son's supposed to be on.
我儿子应该会上电视的
He's in outer space.
他在外太空
This is all the channels we get, Mrs. Lovell.
我们就只有这些频道了，勒维尔太太
It's that damn TV Guide again.
这本烂电视周刊都不准
Ruthless porters.
无情的行李小厮
Savage baggage masters...
狂野的行李大师…
Do they know they're not on the air?
他们知不知道自己没有上电视？
We'll tell them when they get back.
等他们回来再告诉他们
If anyone from the IRS is watching...
如果国税局有人在看的话…
I forgot to file my 1040 return.
我忘了报税
I meant to do it today...
我本来今天要去报的…
That's no joke. They'll jump on him.
这不能开玩笑，国税局会去追查的
Well, folks, let's head on down to the lunar excursion module.
各位，我们下去登月探险小艇看看
Follow me.
跟我来
When we get ready to land on the moon...
我们准备登上月球时…
Fred Haise and I will float through this access tunnel...
佛列德・贺斯跟我 将会飘过这个隧道
into the lunar module, leaving...
进入登月小艇，离开…
EECOM, that stir's gonna be...
电子与环境指令台，要把…
on both H2 and both O2 tanks, is that correct?
氢气桶和氧气桶都搅拌，是否正确？
The spacecraft will remain connected.
太空船将保持接合
Well, folks, as you can probably tell...
各位，你们也许看得出来…
the Aquarius isn't much bigger than a couple of telephone booths.
水瓶号其实没有比两个电话亭大多少
The skin of the LEM in some places...
登月小艇某些部位的外壳…
is only as...
只有…
as thick as a couple of layers...
两层厚的锡箔而已
of tinfoil, and that's all that protects us from the vacuum of space.
我们只靠这薄薄的两层 与太空中的真空隔绝
We get away with this because the LEM is designed only for flight in outer space.
可以这样设计的原因在于，登月小艇 只是为了在外太空飞行而设计
Fred Haise, Renaissance man.
佛列德・贺斯多才多艺
We'll head back up the tunnel now and back into the Odyssey.
我们现在向上穿过隧道 回到奥得赛号
All right, we've returned to the...
好，我们回到了…
Stand by one, Houston.
有状况，休士顿
Gotcha!
受骗了 ！
Houston, that bang you heard was Fred Haise on the cabin repress valve.
休士顿，你刚刚听到的是 佛列德・贺斯在机舱抑制阀上
He gets our hearts going every time with that one.
他每次这样搞都会把我们吓到
We're about to close out the Aquarius...
我们即将封闭水瓶号的出口
and return to the Odyssey.
回到奥得赛号
Our next broadcast will be from Fra Mauro on the surface of the moon.
我们下次将从月球表面的佛拉莫洛转播
So, this is the crew of the Apollo 13...
我们阿波罗13号所有人员…
wishing everyone back on Earth...
祝地球上的各位观众…
a pleasant evening.
有个愉快的夜晚
All right.
好
Daddy was funny.
爸好好玩喔
They might air a few minutes on the news tonight.
他们今晚新闻也许会播个几分钟
You'd think so.
应该会吧
Bye.
掰
Well, between Jack's back taxes and the Fred Haise show...
除了杰克漏税和佛列德耍宝以外…
I'd say that was a pretty successful broadcast.
我觉得这次转播还满成功的
That was an excellent show.
刚才的节目很棒
Thank you very much, Houston.
非常谢谢，休士顿
We've got a couple of housekeeping procedures.
我们有几项常规维修工作要做
We'd like you to roll right to 0-6-0 and null your rates.
请将太空船向右摇到 0-6-0位置，修正差率
Roger that. Rolling right, 0-6-0.
收到，向右摇0-6-0
And then if you could give your oxygen tanks a stir.
然后请将氧气槽摇一摇
Roger that.
收到
We've got a problem here.
这里出了点问题
What did you do? Nothing. I stirred the tanks.
你刚刚干什么？ 没什么，摇一下槽
This is Houston. Say again, please.
这里是休士顿，请重覆
Houston, we have a problem.
休士顿，有麻烦了
We have a main bus B undervolt.
我们主配电盘B电压不足
We've got a lot of thruster activity. What's with the computer?
我们推进器动得很厉害 电脑怎么了？
It just went off line. There's another master alarm.
失去连线 另一个主警铃也响了
Checking the quad. It was no repress valve.
我在检查另一个推进器 那不是控制阀
Maybe it's in quad C. I'll reconfigure the RCS.
也许是C推进器 我来重新设定反应控制系统
We've got a ping light.
一个导航警示灯亮了
We've got multiple caution and warnings. We've got to reset and restart.
出现好几个预警和警示信号 必须重新设定再重新启动
I'm going to SCS.
我进入稳定与控制系统
Flight, their heart rates are skyrocketing.
主任，他们的心跳速率加快很多
EECOM, what's your data telling you? O2 tank two not reading at all.
电子与环境指令台，数据如何？ 氧气槽完全没有读数
Tank one is at 725 psi and falling.
第一槽725psi ，下降中
Fuel cells one and three are...
第一和第三燃料电池…
What's going on? Flight, let me get back to you.
怎么了？ 主任，我待会儿回答你
Flight, GNC. They're all over the place.
主任，导航与领航控制员 到处都有问题
They keep going close to gimbal lock. I keep losing radio signal.
一直接近平衡环的锁定位置 我一直收不到无线电信号
Their antennae must be flipped around.
他们的天线一定折到了
They'll have to do it manually, if at all. One at a time, people.
他们要做的话，只能用手控了 大家不要急，一次一个来
Is this an instrumentation problem or real power loss?
这是仪表出问题还是真的丧失电力？
It's reading a quadruple failure. That can't happen.
它显示冗余安全系统失灵 这不可能啊
It's got to be instrumentation.
一定是仪表板失灵
Get the hatch plugged. A meteor may have hit the LEM.
把舱盖盖上 可能有陨石打到登月小艇了
The tunnel's really torquing with all this movement.
隧道受到震动，扭曲得很厉害
Houston, we had a pretty large bang associated with a master alarm.
休士顿，我们主警铃响了 同时听到很大一声
Shit, it's main bus A.
妈的，是主配电盘A
Main bus A undervolt? Main bus A undervolt down to...
主配电盘A电压不足？ 主配电盘A电压不足，剩下…
It's reading 25-and-a-half. Main bus B is reading zip now.
读数是25. 5 主配电盘B现在的读数是零
We got a wicked shimmy up here.
我们现在摇晃得很厉害
These guys are talking about bangs and shimmies.
他们说有撞击声，摇晃得很厉害
Doesn't sound like instrumentation.
应该不是仪表板的问题
You're breaking up. This hatch won't seal.
你的信号听不清楚了 盖子合不上
Just stow it. If we'd been hit by a meteor, we'd be dead by now.
收起来好了，如果是被陨石打到 我们现在早就没命了
I'm gonna try to get us out of this.
我来想想办法
Houston, did you say switch to omni bravo?
休士顿，你是不是说换成多种模式？
Roger that, 13. The signal strength went way down.
收到，13号 信号强度减弱很多
It's fighting me. What's the story? We keep flirting with gimbal lock.
这船不听我控制，怎么搞的？ 我们一直在修理平衡环
We need a confirmation. What systems are down?
我们需要确认，哪些系统不灵？
SMRCS, Helium one...
维修艇反应控制系统，氦气一号阀…
A and C are barber pole.
A和C都已关闭
Houston, I'm switching over Quad C to main A.
休士顿，我要换到 C推进器和主电源A
Roger that, 13.
收到，13号
Okay, Houston, fuel cell one, fuel cell three.
好，休士顿，一号燃料电池 三号燃料电池
We got a main bus B undervolt, cryo pressure, suit compressor.
我们主电源B电压不足 低温压力，太空衣压缩器
What don't we have? AC bus one, AC bus two.
有哪些警示灯没亮？ 一号和二号高度控制配电盘
Command module computer. O 2 flow high.
指挥小艇电脑，氧气流量高
It may be a caution and warning failure.
也许是预警和警示系统失灵
Houston, we are venting something out into space.
休士顿，我们正往太空中排放东西
I can see it outside window one right now.
我可以从窗口向外看到
It's definitely a gas of some sort.
一定是某种气体
It's got to be the oxygen.
一定是氧气
Roger, Odyssey. We copy your venting.
收到，奥得赛号，消息收到
Give me an alignment. Think about things we can connect.
脑力激荡一下 看看能不能找出这些问题的结合点
Let's start back at the beginning.
从最初开始
Listen up. Quiet down, people.
听好，大家安静
Quiet down!
安静！
Let's stay cool, people.
大家镇静一点
Procedures, I need another computer up in the RTCC.
程序室，我要实时电脑大楼的 另一台电脑
I want everybody to alert your support teams.
我要每个人通知你的支援小组
Wake up anybody you need and get them in here.
把你需要的每个人叫醒 叫到这里来
Let's work the problem, people.
大家同心协力
Let's not make things worse by guessing.
不要用猜的，以免让事情更糟
13, this is Houston. We're going around the room. We'll get you answers.
13号，这里是休士顿，我们在 分头解决问题，然后给你回覆
We keep venting, we're gonna keep hitting the edge of that deadband.
如果继续排气，我们会一直 碰到那块死区边缘
Take a look at the O2 on number one.
看看一号氧气槽的存量
200 pounds and falling.
90公斤，下降中
O2 tank two still zero.
二号氧气槽还是零
218 psi and falling. Is that what you have? Confirm.
一号氧气槽的218psi下降中 你的读数是这样吗？ 请证实
We're seeing the same, 13. Can we review our status, Sy?
我们看到的也是这样，13号 能不能检查我们的状况，赛伊？
Let's look at this thing from a standpoint of status.
从状况角度来看看
What have we got on the spacecraft that's good?
太空船上有哪些方面操作良好？
I'll get back to you, Gene.
我待会儿回覆你，金恩
We're not gonna have power much longer.
我们不久后就没有电源了
The ship's bleeding to death.
这艘太空船能源即将耗尽
Flight? Yeah. Go, EECOM.
主任 是，电子与环境控制员，请说
Flight, I recommend we shut down the reactant valves of the fuel cells.
主任，我建议把燃料电池的 反应阀关上
What the hell good is that gonna do?
那有什么屁用？
If the leak's there, we can isolate it.
如果是从那里泄漏，就能加以隔离
We can save what's left in the tanks, and run on the good cell.
我们能留住槽内剩余能源 用好的电池来操作
You close them, you can't open them again. You can't land on the moon with one cell.
把它关起来，就再也打不开了 只用一颗电池是无法登上月球的
Gene, the Odyssey is dying.
金恩，奥得赛号已经快完蛋了
From my chair here, this is the last option.
以我的观点来看，这是最后的选择
Yeah. Okay, Sy.
好，赛伊
Capcom, let's have them close the reactant valves.
机舱通讯员，让他们把反应阀关上
13, this is Houston.
13号，这里是休士顿
We want you to close react valves on cells one and three. Do you copy?
我们要你把一号和三号电池的 反应阀关上，是否收到？
Are you saying you want the whole smash?
你是说要进行完整步骤吗？
Closing down the react valves for fuel cells shutdown?
把反应阀关上，停用燃料电池？
Shutting down the fuel cells? Did I hear you right?
停用燃料电池？ 我没听错吧？
Yeah, they heard me right.
对，他们没听错
Tell them we think that's the only way they can stop the leak.
告诉他们，我们觉得 只有这样才能防止泄漏
Yeah, Jim...
对，吉姆
we think that closing the react valves may stop the leak.
我们觉得 只有关闭反应阀才能防止泄漏
Did he copy that? Do you copy, Jim?
他收到了吗？ 吉姆，你收到了吗？
Yes, Houston, we copy.
是的，休士顿，我们收到
We just lost the moon.
我们去不成月球了
Okay, Freddo, shut those down.
好，佛列德，停用吧
Let's see what this does.
看看有没有用
If this doesn't work...
如果没有用…
we're not gonna have enough power left to get home.
就没有足够电力回家了
Shit! God damn it!
干！ 妈的！
Houston, O2 on one is still falling.
休士顿，氧气还是在下降中
How long does it take to power up the LEM?
为登月小艇充电要多久时间？
Three hours by the checklist.
按照程序，要三小时
We don't have that much time.
我们没那么多时间
Shit!
干！
Jack, before the batteries completely die on us in here...
杰克，在电池完全耗尽之前…
let's power down everything so we can save as much as we can for re-entry.
我们先把所有电力关闭 节省电力以回到地球
Fifteen minutes of oxygen, that's it. The command module will be dead.
只剩十五分钟的氧气 指挥小艇就完蛋了
Okay, guys, listen up. Here's the drill.
好，各位听好，这样做
We're moving the astronauts to the LEM.
我们把宇航员移到登月小艇上
We've got to get oxygen up there.
要把氧气带到那里去
TELMU, Control, I want emergency power procedure. Essential hardware only.
遥测、 控制室，我要紧急电力程序 只要基本硬体就好
GNC, EECOM, we'll be shutting down the command module at the same time.
导航与领航、 电子与环境 我们要同时停用指挥小艇
We've to transfer the guidance system to another computer.
我们要把导航系统转到另一台电脑
I want those numbers up and ready when they're in position.
他们就定位后 那些数据就要准备好
Transfer all data over the LEM computer before the command module dies.
在指挥小艇失灵之前 把所有数据转移到登月小艇电脑上
The lunar module just became a lifeboat.
登月小艇变成一艘救生船
Odyssey, this is Houston. We need you to power down immediately.
奥得赛号，这里是休士顿 我们要你马上关闭电源
Power up the LEM at the same time, so get somebody over there.
同时把登月小艇电源打开 叫一个人过去
We already have Freddo in the LEM.
佛列德已经到登月小艇上去了
We've got serious time pressure.
我们时间很紧迫
Get the guidance program transferred...
在指挥小艇没电之前…
before you're out of power in the command module...
把导航程序转移过来
or you're not gonna be able to navigate.
否则你就无法航行
How much time? Can you give me a number?
有多少时间？ 能给个数字吗？
We're looking at less than 15 minutes of life support in the Odyssey.
奥得赛号的生命支持系统 只能维持不到15分钟
We've got 15 minutes, Freddo. It's worse than I thought.
我们有15分钟，佛列德 比我想得还要糟
Houston, I've moved from the command module into the LEM.
休士顿，我已经从指挥小艇 移到登月小艇了
If Jack can't get that data transferred before they go dead...
如果杰克无法在他们电力耗尽之前 将数据转移…
They won't know which way they're pointed.
他们就无法知道自己的去向
That's a bad way to fly. I'll be in 210 if you need me.
这样航行很危险 我到210室去，有事告诉我
Houston, this is 13. Are you back with me now?
休士顿，这是13号 收到我的通讯吗？
Aquarius, this is Houston. You now have about 12 minutes to power up.
水瓶号，这里是休士顿 你现在有12分钟时间的电力
I can't see any stars. Man, there's a lot of debris floating around out there.
我看不到星星，天哪 好多残骸漂来漂去
Houston, I have completed the steps on Page 15.
休士顿，我完成了第15页的步骤
I'm ready to power down the computer.
我准备把电脑关机了
I'm gonna need your gimbal angles, Jack, before you shut down the computer!
在你电脑关机之前 我需要你的平衡环角度，杰克
Okay, Jim.
好，吉姆
I need this back before they power down.
电源关闭前要获得这个值
All right, I got it. Hold on.
好，我知道了，等等
Houston, our computer is up. Roger. Stand by.
休士顿，我们电脑开启了 收到，待命
Jack, we need to proceed with steps 12 through 17 quickly.
杰克，我们必须立刻进行 12至17步骤
You're down to about eight minutes remaining.
你只剩8分钟时间
Fuel cell pump's off. O2 fans, tank two off.
燃料电池帮浦关闭 氧气扇、 二号槽关闭
Okay, Houston, check me. I have completed the gimbal conversions...
好，休士顿，告诉我 我已完成了平衡环转换
but I need a double check of the arithmetic.
但我需要再检查一次算术数据
Yeah, you can go, Jim. The roll CAL angle is minus two.
好，吉姆，请说 转换校准角度是负二度
Lunar module roll is 355.57.
登月小艇左右是355. 57
Pitch. 1678, correction.
上下： 1678，修正
Pitch.167. 78.
上下： 167. 78
Yaw is 351.87.
偏率是351. 87
Stand by. We're checking it.
稍待，检查中
We've got negative visibility in our star field...
我们这里星际视野很差
and if this paperwork isn't right, who knows where we'll end up out here.
如果这些计算值出错 那谁知道我们最后会跑到哪里去
Looks good, Flight.
看来不错，主任
It's all right. Good here.
没问题 这里好了
He's good, Andy. We'll go on those numbers.
他好了，安迪 就用这些计算值来做
You're good. Log them in.
你好了 载入，佛列德
Turn off the IMU. Switch to SCS.
关掉惯性测量机件，换成稳控系统
Stand by. Over.
待命，完毕
It's a great day in New York. It's girl watchers' weather.
纽约今天天气真好 正适合去看美眉
I like the ingenious girl watchers who wear Con Edison helmets...
我很喜欢这些看美眉的人 他们很聪明，带着爱迪生牌的头盔…
and dig trenches in the street to get a better view.
在街上挖壕沟，找个好角度来看
But speaking of girl watching...
但提到看美眉
did you know that our first bachelor astronaut is on his way to the moon?
你知道我们第一个单身的宇航员 正准备上月球去吗？
Is it Swigert? Yeah, first bachelor.
是不是史威格？ 对 第一个单身宇航员
They say he's the kind who has a girl in every port. He has that reputation.
据说他在每个太空站都有一个美眉 出了名的花心
He's sort of foolishly optimistic, taking nylons and Hershey bars to the moon.
他还傻傻的，乐观得很 把丝袜跟巧克力棒带到月球去
Did you read that three million...
报上说，3百万…
What do you say? Less viewers or fewer viewers?
你会怎么说？ 是低3百万还是 少3百万观众？
Three million fewer viewers...
这次看太空转播的观众…
watched the space shot than did the last one.
比上次少3百万人
Here is ABC science editor Jules Bergman.
这是ABC科学新闻记者朱尔斯柏格曼
The Apollo 13 spacecraft has lost all electrical power...
阿波罗13号太空船已失去所有电力
astronauts Jim Lovell, Fred Haise and Jack Swigert...
宇航员吉姆・勒维尔、 佛列德・贺斯 和杰克・史威格…
are making their way to the lunar module...
正前往登月小艇
using it as a lifeboat so they'll have electrical power...
用它作为救生船以获取电力…
for their radios on the command module.
来为指挥小艇的无线电供电
Apollo 13 is apparently also losing breathing oxygen...
阿波罗13号显然也失去呼吸的氧气
Slow down. An "electrical failure." What exactly does that mean?
等等， “电气失灵” 到底是什么意思？
The emergency ruled out a lunar landing...
这次紧急事故使他们 完全失去登陆月球的机会
and could endanger the lives of the astronauts...
并可能造成宇航员生命危险
if the LEM oxygen supply, plus whatever is left of the command module's oxygen...
如果登月小艇氧气以及 指挥小艇所剩的氧气…
can't last them until they can get back to Earth.
不够让他们返回地球
What do you mean, "no immediate danger"?
什么叫 “无立即危险” ？
I heard they're losing oxygen. Can they get back?
我听说他们丧失氧气 他们回得来吗？
The LEM's descent rocket engine will be used to abort the mission...
登月小艇的下降火箭引擎将用来 取消此次任务…
and get them safely back to Earth.
让他们平安返回地球
Recapping what has happened.
再把本报导简述一次
The Apollo 13 astronauts may be in grave danger.
阿波罗13号宇航员 可能处于极度危险状态
No, don't give me that NASA bullshit!
别拿航太总署的屁话哄我
I want to know what's happening with my husband!
我要知道我先生怎么了 ！
We want to switch control to Aquarius.
我们现在要把控制移到水瓶号
Roger that. Houston, wait!
收到 休士顿，等等！
You're down to about five minutes now.
你们只剩约5分钟了
Be aware our RCS isn't up here yet. We have no attitude control on Aquarius.
注意到，我们这里的反应控制系统 还没启用，水瓶号无法控制高度
They don't have control? Did we miss a step here?
他们无法控制？ 我们漏了一个步骤吗？
Control, what the hell happened? I don't know. We need more time.
控制室，搞什么鬼啊？ 我不知道，我们需要多点时间
We're out of whack.
我们歪掉了
I'm trying to pitch down. We're yawing to the left.
我设法往下，却一直往左边斜过去
Why can't I null this out?
为什么无法稳定下来？
She wasn't designed to fly attached like this.
登月小艇不是为了 这样连结飞行而设计的
It's like flying with a dead elephant on our back.
好像带着一只死象一起飞一样
Flight, Guidance. We're getting close to center here.
主任，导航与领航 我们非常靠近中心点了
Watch that middle gimbal. We don't want you tumbling off into space.
注意中间的平衡环 我们可不希望你们跌入太空中
Inform them I'm well aware of the goddamn gimbals!
告诉他们，我很留意那些 讨厌的平衡环！
Roger that. I don't need to hear the obvious.
收到 废话不用多说
I can see the frapping eight-ball!
我看得到那颗小球！
Andy, we're on VOX.
安迪，我们用声控麦克风了
Aquarius, this is Houston. We've got you both on VOX.
水瓶号，这里是休士顿 我们让你们两边都用声控麦克风
You want us to go to VOX?
你要我们也用声控麦克风？
You have a hot mike. We are reading everything you say.
你有个声控麦克风 你说的我们都听见了
Sorry, Jim.
抱歉，吉姆
It's only by a very narrow margin...
勒维尔、 贺斯和史威格…
that we're going to get Lovell, Haise and Swigert back alive.
生还的机会非常渺茫
I'm sorry. Jeffrey's calling for you.
抱歉，杰佛利打电话找你
The terseness of Kraft and the grim lines of Jim McDivitt.
卡夫并不多说 吉姆・麦迪维语调悲观，看来…
This has been a very close call. We're not out of the woods yet.
这次情况非常不妙 我们尚未脱离危险
Why are so many people here?
为什么这么多人来？
Your dad's flying his mission.
你爸爸在出飞行任务呀
He said he was going to get me a moon rock.
他说要带一块月球岩石给我
Right.
对
Something broke on your daddy's spaceship...
有东西打到爸爸的太空船
and he's gonna have to turn around before he even gets to the moon.
他要先回头再去月球
Was it the door?
是门出了问题吗？
13, we still show that venting pushing you around.
13号，我们还是显示 排气的情况把你们推来推去
How you doing? Houston, Aquarius.
你的状况如何？ 休士顿，水瓶号
We've had to learn how to fly all over again, but we are doing better now.
我们得重新学习如何飞行 但已经好些了
Roger that, Aquarius. Have him close it out.
收到，水瓶号 叫他结束程序
Jack, we can close out your procedure now.
杰克，我们现在可以 把你们的程序结束了
Do we know for sure that we can power this thing back up?
我们确定能让太空船 重新获得动力吗？
It's gonna get awfully cold in here.
这里会变得很冷
Copy that, Jack. We'll just have to deal with that later.
收到，杰克，这点待会儿再解决
Computer off. We're clear.
电脑关机 我们关机了
We're going to the LEM.
转到登月小艇
We confirm shutdown, Jack.
我们证实停机了，杰克
Lunar module now in control.
现在由登月小艇控制
Roger that, Houston. This is Odyssey signing off.
收到，休士顿 奥得赛号结束无线电通讯
Freddo, we're gonna have to execute some sort of burn.
佛列德，我们势必要发射火箭
It's just a matter of when.
只是早晚的问题
Did they shut us all down in there? Yeah.
他们把那边的动力都去除了吗？ 对
Didn't think we'd be back in here so soon.
没想到我们会这么快回来
Houston, how far off course do you project we are? Over.
休士顿，你预计我们 离航道有多远？ 完毕
Okay, people, listen up!
好，大家听好！
Gentlemen, I want you all to forget the flight plan.
各位，我要大家 不要再管飞行计划
From this moment on, we are improvising a new mission.
从现在起，我们重新拟一个新任务
Sorry about that. We'll get somebody to look at that.
很抱歉，我们会找人去处理
How do we get our people home?
如何才能让他们回家？
They are here.
他们在这里
Do we turn them around, direct abort? Yes!
要叫他们调头，直接取消任务？ 对！
No, sir! We get them on a free-return trajectory.
不行！ 应该让他们绕到月球后 再被地心引力拉回来
It's the option with the fewest question marks for safety.
这样是最安全的选择
I agree. We use the moon's gravity to slingshot them around.
我同意，我们使用月球的引力 来牵引他们绕着月球转
No, the LEM will not support three guys for that amount of time.
不行，登月小艇无法支持3个人 那么久的时间
I think we've got to do a direct abort. We do an about-face, bring the guys right home.
我觉得应该直接回头，180度回转 让他们直接回来
Get them back soon. Absolutely.
绝对要让他们快点回来
We don't even know if the Odyssey's engine's working.
我们甚至不知道奥得赛号的引擎 是否还能用
If there's been serious damage to the craft... They blow up and they die!
如果太空船已经严重损坏… 他们就会爆炸，一命呜呼！
That is not the argument! We're talking about time!
这不是重点！ 我是指时间！
Not whether these guys... I'm not gonna sugarcoat this for you!
而不是这些人会不会… 我不想讲好听的话来骗你！
Okay, hold it. Let's hold it down.
好，等等，不要吵
The only engine we've got with enough power for a direct abort...
我们的引擎中唯一有足够动力 能直接回头的…
is the SPS on the service module.
是维修小艇上的维修推进系统
It could have been damaged in an explosion...
在爆炸中它可能已经受损了
so let's consider that engine dead.
所以假设它已经失灵
We light it up, could blow the whole works.
如果发动它，整艘船可能会爆炸
Just too risky. We're not gonna take that chance.
太危险了 我们不能冒这个险
The only thing the command module's good for is re-entry.
指挥小艇的唯一功用 是返回地球
That leaves us with the LEM, which means free-return trajectory.
因此我们只剩登月小艇 所以应该让他们绕月球
Once we get the guys around the moon...
让他们绕过月球之后…
we'll fire up the LEM engine, make a long burn...
再启动登月小艇引擎 做长时间燃烧
pick up some speed, and get them home as quick as we can.
加快速度，尽快让他们回来
Gene, I'm wondering what the Grumman guys think about this.
金恩，我不知道登月小艇 设计小组的看法如何
We can't make any guarantees. We designed the LEM to land on the moon...
我们无法保证 我们设计登月小艇的目的是登陆月球
not fire the engine for course corrections.
而不是开动引擎，修正轨道
Well, unfortunately, we're not landing on the moon, are we?
反正我们现在也无法登陆 月球了，对不对？
I don't care what anything was designed to do. I care about what it can do.
我不管那东西的设计目的是什么 我只管它能做什么
So let's get to work. Let's lay it out, okay?
所以大家一起努力 好好计划，好吗？
Capcom, Flight, he says it will be ready in time.
机舱通讯员，主任 他说可以及时完成准备
DAY 4 After this burn, we've got to build time in the flight plan for them to get sleep.
第4天燃烧之后，我们必须在飞行计划中 安排让他们有足够时间睡眠
Run it by the FAO. I've run it by the FAO.
我会向飞行实验与控制员建议 我已经建议了
Do we know how long we're gonna fire that burn?
我们知道应该燃烧多久吗？
He wanted a quote from a flight director. Who wanted a quote?
他要问飞行主任成功机会有多少 谁要知道成功机会？
The President. The President?
总统 总统？
Nixon. He wants our odds.
尼克森，他要知道成功机会
We are not losing the crew.
我们绝对要让他们活着回来
NASA I gotta give him odds. Five to one against? Three to one?
金恩，我得告诉他成功的机会 六分之一？ 四分之一？
I don't think they're that good. We are not losing those men.
恐怕没这么乐观 我们绝不放弃
How long are they gonna have to burn the engine PC + 2?
他们在通过近月点两小时后 要燃烧引擎多久？
Look, tell him three to one.
告诉他成功机会是四分之一
Expect loss of signal in less than one minute.
预计1分钟内将会失去信号
When we pick you back up we will have your PC + 2 burn data.
当再次接收到信号时 会给你们近月点2小时后燃烧的数据
Okay. Roger that, Houston. We'll hear from you again at acquisition of signal.
好，收到，休士顿 我们在收到你信号后再等你消息
You wanna look?
要不要看看？
Oh, look at that.
好漂亮
Aquarius, that's 30 seconds until loss of signal.
水瓶号，在30秒后终止信号
Mare Tranquillitatis.
宁静海
Neil and Buzz's old neighborhood.
阿姆斯特朗和阿尔德林就在这里着陆
Coming up on Mount Marilyn.
接下来是玛丽莲山
Jim, you gotta take a look at this.
吉姆，你得来看看这个
I've seen it.
我看过了
Aquarius, this is Houston.
水瓶号，这里是休士顿
We expect loss of signal in approximately ten seconds.
我们预计约再过10秒终止信号
So long, Earth. Catch you on the flip side.
再见，地球，到了反面再见
When you go into the moon's shadow... and the moon is between you and the sun...
当你进入月球阴影时 月球挡在你和太阳之间
you see stars that are more brilliant than anything you've ever seen...
此时看到的星星比在地球上 最晴朗的夜空中所看到的…
on the clearest nights here on Earth.
还要更明亮
And then you pass into the lunar sunrise over the lunar surface.
然后你就在月球表面上看日出
It must be an awe-inspiring sight. I can't wait to see it myself.
景象一定是非常壮观 我等不及要目睹
The problem now is not so much a question of adequate oxygen supply...
现在的问题不在于 氧气补给是否足够…
but it is the rate of consumption of water...
而是水的消耗率…
which is vitally needed for the cooling operations...
为了使冷却操作能维持电力系统…
to maintain the electronic systems...
这是绝对必要的
Look, it's Fra Mauro.
你看，是佛拉莫洛
I can see our landing site.
我看得到我们的着陆点
Look at the Tsiolkovsky Crater.
看看希欧考夫斯基陨石坑
I can't believe how bright the ejecta blanket is.
我真不敢相信那层残骸居然这么亮
It's like snow. It's beautiful.
好像雪，真美
That's Mare Imbrium to the north.
那个北边是雨海
13, this is Houston.
13号，这里是休士顿
We're reading your telemetry. It's good to see you again.
我们收到你的遥测资料 很高兴又见到你
Good to see you, too, Houston.
很高兴见到你，休士顿
We are picking you up at a velocity of 7,062 feet per second...
资料显示你们距月球104公里处…
at a distance from the moon of 56 nautical miles.
以每秒2152公尺的速度行驶
Stand by for your PC + 2 burn data.
准备接收你们近月点2小时后的 燃烧数据
Got to tell you, I had an itch to take this baby down, do some prospecting.
我得告诉你们，我真想驾着这小艇 下去探勘一下
Damn, we were close.
妈的，就差这么一点点
Gentlemen, what are your intentions?
各位，你们在想什么？
I'd like to go home.
我想回家
We got a burn coming up.
我们就要燃烧引擎了
We're gonna need a contingency if we lose comm with Houston.
我们要一个应急计划划 以防万一与休士顿无法通讯
Let's get an idea where we stand on the consumables.
检查一下消耗品剩下多少
Jack, get into the Odyssey...
杰克，到奥得赛号上…
and bag up all the water you can before it freezes in there.
把所有水都搜刮来 免得到时在里面结冰
Let's go home.
回家了
Aquarius, we got some PC + 2 burn data for you fellas.
水瓶号，我们有一些 近月点后燃烧引擎的数据给你们
So you're telling me you can only give our guys 45 hours?
你说你只能给他们45小时？
That brings them to about there.
那只能让他们到这里
Gentlemen, that's not acceptable.
各位，这是不够的
Gene, we've got to talk about power.
金恩，我们要看看电力
Guys! power is everything!
各位，电力是最重要的！
power is everything. What do you mean?
电力是最重要的！ 什么意思？
Without it, they don't talk to us, correct their trajectory...
没有电力，他们就无法跟我们通讯 修正轨道
they don't turn the heat shield around.
无法让热隔层调头
We gotta turn everything off. Now. They're not gonna make it to re-entry.
现在必须把一切关掉 他们无法回到地球
What do you mean, "everything"? If everything's on, the LEM draws 60 amps.
你所谓 “一切” 是什么意思？ 开启一切，登月小艇会耗费60安培
At that rate, in 16 hours the batteries are dead, not 45.
以这个速率，不用等45小时 16小时内电池就完蛋了
And so is the crew. We gotta get them down to 12 amps.
人员也完蛋了 必须叫他们关到只剩12安培
Twelve amps? How many?
12安培？ 多少？
You can't run a vacuum cleaner on 12 amps, John.
约翰，12安培连吸尘器都没法用
We gotta turn off the radars, cabin heater...
必须关掉雷达、 机舱暖气…
instrument displays, guidance computer, everything.
仪表显示器、导航电脑等一切设备
Guidance computer? What if they need to do another burn?
导航电脑？ 如果要再燃烧一次怎么办？
They won't know which way they're pointed.
他们会找不到目的地的方向
The more time we talk, the more juice they waste.
我们讲得越久，他们消耗的电力越多
I've looked at data for the past hour.
我看了上个钟头的数据
That's the deal? That's the deal.
情况就是这样？ 情况就是这样
Okay, John. The minute we finish the burn, we'll power down the LEM.
好，约翰，我们一完成燃烧 就把登月小艇动力关闭
All right.
好
Now, in the meantime, we're gonna have a frozen command module up there.
现在，我们的指挥小艇 会暂时很冷
Soon, we'll have to power it up using nothing but the re-entry batteries.
我们很快必须只用返回地球的电池 来为它提供动力
That's never been tried before. We've never even simulated it before.
从来没有人这样做过 甚至没有模拟过
Well, we're gonna have to figure it out.
我们必须想出办法来
I want people in our simulators working re-entry scenarios.
我要人员到模拟机中 拟出返回地球的草案
I want you to find every engineer who designed every switch, circuit...
我要你们去找到设计太空船中每个 按钮和电路、 电晶体和灯泡的…
transistor and light bulb up there.
每位工程师
Then, talk to the guy in the assembly line who actually built the thing.
然后，去问问生产线上 实际制造这些东西的人
Find out how to squeeze every amp out of both of these goddamn machines.
找出如何从这两艘小艇上 榨出一安培的电力
I want this mark all the way back to Earth with time to spare.
我要这个点回到地球后 还有多余的时间
We never lost an American in space.
美国人从未在太空中丧生
We're sure as hell not gonna lose one on my watch.
在我的领导下 我更不允许牺牲任何人
Failure is not an option.
只准成功，不准失败
What? Good, you're not dead.
干嘛？ 好，你还没死
I've been trying to get in touch with you for 45 minutes.
我已经跟你联络45分钟了
Jesus, what're you doing here?
妈的，你来干嘛？
I gotta get you in the simulator. We got a ship to land.
我要你进模拟机，帮太空船着陆
What? There's been an explosion.
什么？ 刚刚发生了爆炸
Oxygen tanks are gone, two fuel cells gone, command module's shut down.
氧气桶失灵，两个燃料电池失灵 指挥小艇已经停用
What about the crew? Fine so far.
人员呢？ 人员目前没事
Trying to keep them alive in the LEM.
正设法让他们留在登月小艇上
We'll have to shut that down pretty soon, too.
但很快也要切断电力了
We got a lot of people working the numbers on this one.
很多人在帮忙想办法
Nobody's too sure how much power we'll have for re-entry.
没人能确定需要多少电力 才回得来
The command module will be frozen up pretty good by then.
到时指挥小艇八成结冻了
If you see this ammeter rise over 20 at any point, power-up is no good.
如果你在任何时候看到 这个指针超过20，电力就不够了
If it spikes, that's sayonara for the guidance computer.
如果用电量太高 导航电脑就完蛋了
Our guys can't re-enter, okay?
回不来了，懂吗？
How much power do we have to play with?
我们剩多少电力可用？
Barely enough to run this coffee pot for nine hours.
只能让这个咖啡壶再煮9个钟头
Go. Ken Mattingly just got here.
请说 肯马丁利刚到这里
Copy. He's here.
收到，他来了
They've lost heat since the accident.
自从发生意外，他们就一直失温
They'll start getting water condensation on the control panels.
他们的控制板上会开始凝结水气
Glad you're here. You know what's going on?
还好你来了，状况了解吗？
John's brought me up to speed.
约翰告诉我了
What's left in the batteries? We don't know.
电池的电还剩多少？ 不知道
We gotta get started on some shortcuts for power-up.
我们得抄捷径来获取电力
You know how short?
怎么做？
It's all in the sequencing. If we can skip whatever we don't absolutely need...
从序列中着手 如果能跳过不完全必要的部份…
turn things on in the right order, maybe... I agree.
也许能以正确的顺序来启用电力… 我同意
You started on a procedure? Engineers have tried, but it's your ship.
你们开始进行程序了吗？ 工程师已经试了，但还是你最清楚
We gotta get you in there. Okay.
我们要让你进去 好
Frank, I need the sim cold and dark.
法兰克，我要让模拟机又冷又暗
Give me the exact conditions they've got in there now.
给我他们目前的实际状况
I need status of every instrument. You got it.
我要每件设备的状态 没问题
I need a flashlight. That's not what they have up there.
我要手电筒 他们没有这种手电筒
Don't give me anything they don't have on board.
不要给我他们船上没有的东西
Let's get this show on the road. Put him in space, fellas.
开始进行吧 各位，把他放入太空
Okay, Houston, the quad-heater circuit breakers are open.
好，休士顿，推进器加热机的 断路器打开了
Copy that.
收到
We'll use the forward omni when the Earth's in the window...
从窗外看到地球后 我们就用前方的多方天线
and we're switching to aft omni when we see the moon.
看到月球后再换成后方的天线
We copy that, 13.
收到，13号
Aquarius, we don't want you to make any more waste dumps.
水瓶号，请不要再排出任何废物
The venting may push you off course.
排出时可能会把你推离轨道
Oh, Christ. What's up?
妈的 怎么了？
No more waste dumps. We're just gonna have to store it.
不能排出去，只好存起来了
Jack, we're gonna need some more urine bags.
杰克，我们还要一些储尿袋
Okay, Houston, that leaves us with just the computer...
好，休士顿 现在我们只剩一台电脑
which I'm shutting down now.
现在我要关掉这台电脑了
And that's it.
就这样了
We just put Sir Isaac Newton in the driver's seat.
让牛顿的万有引力来主导一切吧
Is it a.m. Or p. M?
现在是早上还是晚上？
A.m. Very, very a.m.
早上，非常早
Haise is running a temperature, and no one has slept.
贺斯有点发烧，没有人在睡觉
I can't order these guys to go to sleep. Could you sleep up there?
我总不能命令他们去睡觉 要是你，你睡得着吗？
It's gonna get awful cold in there for those guys.
他们会很冷的
Gene, we have a situation brewing with the carbon dioxide.
金恩，我们有二氧化碳的问题
We got a CO2 filter problem on the lunar module.
登月小艇的二氧化碳滤纲有问题
Five filters on the LEM. For two guys for a day and a half.
登月小艇上有5个滤纲 可供两个人用一天半
I told the doc... We're up to eight on the gauges.
我告诉过… 我们的读数已经高达8了
Anything over 15 and you get impaired judgment, blackouts...
只要超过15 就会导致判断力减弱、 昏迷
the beginnings of brain asphyxia.
开始脑缺氧
What about scrubbers in the command module?
指挥小艇上的滤器呢？
They take square cartridges. The ones on the LEM are round.
它是用方的滤器 登月小艇上的滤器是圆的
Tell me this isn't a government operation.
天啊，政府部门协调得还真有效率
This just isn't a contingency we've remotely looked at.
我们的应急计划 完全没考虑到这点
Those CO2 levels will be getting toxic.
二氧化碳浓度会越来越有害
I suggest you gentlemen invent a way to put a square peg in a round hole. Rapidly.
我建议各位找出方法，把方的滤器 放入圆的洞中，动作要快
Okay, people, listen up!
好，大家听着！
The people upstairs have handed us this one, and we gotta come through.
上头丢给我们一个任务 我们要尽力完成
We gotta find a way to make this...
我们要想办法把这个…
fit into the hole for this...
放入这里
using nothing but that.
只能用这些材料
Let's get organized. Let's build a filter.
开始整理吧 好，我们来造一个滤器
Better get some coffee going, too.
最好也去煮咖啡
The Haise family lives in El Lago, Texas.
贺斯一家住在德州爱尔拉哥市
His wife, Mary, is from Biloxi, Mississippi.
他太太玛丽来自密西西比州比拉希市
When Fred Haise was growing up in Biloxi, he may have looked ahead to a fine family...
佛列德・贺斯在比拉希长大时 也许曾想要美满的家庭生活…
but he never dreamt of flying.
但从未梦想飞行
I'd never flown before I went into the service...
我在服役前从未飞行过…
and I only went into the flying business as a means to getting a commission...
宇航员 小佛列德・贺斯 我开始飞行时，只是为了 拿一张任职令…
Good morning. Henry. Don't you ever sleep?
早安 亨利，你怎么不睡？
I have a request from the news people.
新闻记者想要你帮个忙
They're out front here and they want to put a transmitter up on the lawn.
他们在外面，想要在草地上 搭起发射台
Transmitter?
发射台？
It's kind of a tower for a live broadcast.
就是一种现场转播用的塔台
I thought they didn't care about the mission. They didn't even run Jim's show.
我以为他们根本不关心这次任务 他们根本没有播出吉姆的节目
Well, it's more dramatic now. Suddenly people are...
不过现在比较有戏剧性了 观众突然…
If landing on the moon wasn't dramatic enough, why should not landing on it be?
如果登陆月球还不够有戏剧性 登陆不成怎会有戏剧性？
Look, I realize how hard this is, Marilyn...
玛丽莲，我知道你很担心…
but the whole world is caught up in it.
但全世界都很关心这件事
It's the biggest story since... No, Henry.
好久没有这么大的新闻… 不，亨利
Those people don't put one piece of equipment on my lawn.
这些人连一件装备 也别想放在我的草地上
If they have a problem with that, they can take it up with my husband.
如果他们不服，可以去找我先生理论
He'll be home on Friday.
他星期五就会回家
DAY 5
第5天
Hey, Fred.
嘿，佛列德
It's too cold in there.
那里太冷了
That's a nice one of Mary.
玛丽这张照片很好看
You don't look too good, Freddo. I'll survive.
佛列德，你看起来不太好 我死不了
Aspirin in the medical kit. I took some.
医药盒里有阿斯匹灵 我吃过了
Jim, I'm all right.
吉姆，我没事
It was an accident, Mary getting pregnant.
我不小心，让玛丽怀孕
You should have seen the look on my face when she told me.
她告诉我的时候 你真该看看我的表情
Well, that has a tendency to happen.
事情总是这样的
I wonder if it's a boy or a girl.
不知道是男是女
You're gonna find out soon enough.
马上就知道了
Sure.
对
I never dreamed I'd ever get to do something like this.
我从未梦想过能做这种事
Come up here on a real mission.
上来参与实际任务
Most of the guys I graduated high school with...
跟我同届毕业的大部份高中同学…
never even left home, and here I am.
从未离开家乡，而我现在却在这里
Oh, yeah.
对
Here you are.
你在这里
It hurts when I urinate.
我尿尿时会痛
Well, you're not getting enough water. I'm drinking my ration the same as you.
你喝的水不够多 我喝的水量和你一样多
I think old Swigert gave me the clap.
我想史威格大概把淋病传染给我了
He's been pissing in my relief tube.
他用我的小尿管来小便
Well, that will be a hot one at the debriefing for the flight surgeon.
跟医官提报时 这可有得说了
That's another first for America's space program.
美国太空计划史上头一遭
Listen, I've been going over some stuff...
对了，我在检查一些东西
and I'm a little worried about this cold affecting our battery efficiency.
我有点担心低温会影响我们电池效率
We quit heating the glycol to save water and power, so that's not helping.
我们为了省水省电而不再 将防冻剂保温，所以情况更糟
Could cost us amp hours on the back end?
这会在最后几小时 消耗电力吗？
That's a possibility. I've been going over the numbers.
有可能 我又检查了一次数据
Have they called up with a re-entry plan yet?
他们把返回地球的计划传过来了吗？
We're coming in too shallow... We're working on it.
我们接近地球的角度太缓… 我们在努力中
I can't remember the ratio to temperature. We got no references on board.
我不记得温度的比率 船上没有参考数据
Let's see if Houston can pull up the mil specs...
等看看休士顿是否能提供军队规格…
Listen, they gave us too much Delta V. They had us burn too long.
听好，他们给了太大的速度变更值 让我们燃烧过久了
At this rate we'll skip right out of the atmosphere, and never get back.
照这样下去，我们会跳出大气层 永远回不去了
What are you talking about? How'd you figure that?
你在说什么？ 怎么得出这个结论的？
I can add.
我会加法
Many Phds are working on this. Houston says we're on the money.
许多博士在一起研究 休士顿说我们这样没错
What if they made a mistake and there was no way to reverse it?
如果他们有错而且无法改正呢？
You think they'd tell us?
你想他们会承认吗？
There's no reason! What do you mean? That's bullshit!
他们不用告诉我们！ 你是什么意思？ 放屁！
There's 1,000 things that have to happen in order.
有一千项程序必须按照顺序做
We are on number eight. You're talking about number 692.
我们只做到第8项 你就在谈第692项了
In the meantime, I'm trying to tell you we're coming in too fast.
我只是想告诉你们，我们冲得太快了
I think they know it, and that's why we don't have a re-entry plan.
我想他们也知道，所以才无法 向我们提供返回地球的计划
That's duly noted. Thank you, Jack.
我知道了，谢谢，杰克
God damn this piece of shit!
妈的这块废物！
This piece of shit's gonna get you home.
你还得靠这块废物才回得了家呢
That's because that's the only thing we've got left, Jack!
因为我们只剩这块东西了，杰克！
What are you saying, Fred? I think you know what I'm saying.
你在说什么，佛列德？ 我想你知道我在说什么
Now wait a minute. All I did was stir those tanks.
等等，我只不过是 摇摇那些氧气槽而已
What was the gauge reading before you hit the switch?
你按下开关前，上面的读数是多少？
Don't tell me how to fly the CM! They brought me in to do a job!
我开指挥小艇，还用不到你来教！ 是他们要我出任务的！
They asked me to stir the damn tanks, and I stirred the tanks!
妈的，是他们叫我摇氧气槽 我才摇的！
Stop kicking yourself in the ass. This is not my fault!
不要自责！ 这不是我的错！
No one is saying it is.
没人说是你的错
If I'm in the left-hand seat when the call comes up, I stir the tanks.
如果刚好是我坐在左边 我接到命令，我也会去摇的
Well, tell him that.
他就是不信
I just asked you what the gauge was reading, and you don't know!
我只是问你读数多少，你却不知道！
Look, we're not doing this, gentlemen.
两位，不要再吵了
We're not bouncing off the walls for ten minutes...
再这样激动下去…
because we'll just end up with the same problems!
一样解决不了问题！
Try to figure out how to stay alive!
想办法保命要紧！
Aquarius, this is Houston.
水瓶号，这里是休士顿
Are we on VOX? No, we're not on VOX.
我们用声控麦克风吗？ 不是
Yeah, Houston, this is Aquarius. Go ahead.
好，休士顿，这里是水瓶号，请说
Yeah, Jim, could you check your CO 2 gauge for us?
好，吉姆，能不能帮我们 看看二氧化碳读数？
We were just looking at that.
我们刚刚才看过
Our CO2 measurement has jumped four notches in the last hour.
二氧化碳读数在过去1小时内 上升了4格
That can't be right. I went over those numbers three times.
不可能吧 这些数据我检查了3次
Jim, that sounds about right. We were expecting that.
吉姆，那应该没错 与我们预期的一样
That's very comforting to know, Houston. What do we do about it?
这下可好了，休士顿 怎么办呢？
Jim, we're working on a procedure down here for you.
吉姆，我们在帮你研究一个程序
Do you copy? Oh, Christ.
收到吗？ 天哪
All right, we're standing by for those procedures.
好，我们准备收听这个程序
Christ, I know why my numbers are wrong.
老天，我知道我的数目为什么不对了
I only figured it for two people.
我只计算了两个人
Maybe I should just hold my breath.
也许我应该屏住呼吸
The deadly CO 2 gas is literally poisoning... the astronauts with every breath in and out.
随着每一次呼吸 宇航员都受到致命的二氧化碳毒害
Heads up.
小心
Go.
来
Heads up, people. Look out now.
大家小心
What's this? That's what they gotta make.
这是什么？ 他们就是要做这个
I hope you got the procedures. Right here.
希望你有个程序给我 就在这里
That's it?
就这样？
All right, Aquarius, this is Houston.
好，水瓶号，这里是休士顿
Do you have a flight plan up there?
你那里有一份飞行计划吗？
Affirmative, Andy. Jack's got one right here.
有，安迪，杰克这里有一份
Okay, we have an unusual procedure for you here.
好，我这里有个特别的程序给你
We need you to rip the cover off.
请你把它的封面撕下来
He wants you to rip the cover off the flight plan.
他要你把飞行计划的封面撕下来
With pleasure.
照办
The other materials you'll need are...
你需要的其它材料包括…
a lithium hydroxide canister...
一个氢氧化锂滤毒罐…
Two lithium hydroxide canisters, I'm sorry...
抱歉，是两个氢氧化锂滤毒罐…
a roll of gray tape. Duct tape.
一卷灰胶带 万能胶带
Duct tape. You need an LCG bag... Two LCG bags...
万能胶带，你需要一个液冷衣的袋子 两个液冷衣的袋子
the red suit hoses, and you've got the flight plan cover.
红接头管，然后再加上 飞行计划的封面
What about their level of carbon dioxide?
他们的二氧化碳浓度如何？
It's climbing.
越来越高
You're saying that they're almost out of breathable air?
你是说他们可呼吸的空气 即将耗尽吗？
Wait a second. That's not what he said. He said we're working on it.
等等，他不是这样讲的 他说我们在努力中
You want to cut the duct tape three feet long.
你把万能胶带切1公尺下来
Tell him to use his arm. Just use your arm.
叫他用手臂 用你的手臂
An arm's length. I see what you're getting at.
大约手臂长 我知道你的意思了
Jack, tear that piece of tape down the middle lengthwise.
杰克，把那块胶带沿中间撕下来
All right? Hold on, Houston.
可以吗？ 等等，休士顿
While the astronauts appear to have enough oxygen to keep them alive...
宇航员显然有足够的氧气维生
one thing they have too much of is carbon dioxide.
但他们的二氧化碳太多
With each breath, the three men expel...
每一次呼吸，3个人…
more of the poisonous gas into the lunar module cockpit...
在登月小艇座舱中所 排出的这种有毒气体就越来越多
and the scrubbers intended to keep the atmosphere breathable...
用来净化空气的过滤器…
are quickly becoming saturated.
已经快速饱和
Oh, shit, I tore it.
妈的，我扯裂了
Houston, what do we do if we ripped the bag? can we tape it?
休士顿，我们把袋子扯裂了怎么办？ 可以帖起来吗？
They just tore the bag. Oh, no.
他们把袋子扯裂了 唉呀
Stand by. What should I tell them to do? They should have one more bag left.
稍待，应该叫他们怎么做？ 他们应该还剩一个袋子
But they've still got a long way to come...
但他们还有很长的一段路
and are now working on backup facilities, their emergency facilities.
我们正在处理后备设施 他们的紧急设施
The problem is, if anything more goes wrong, they're in real trouble.
问题是，如果再出问题，就很麻烦了
As most of you are aware, there is no rescue possible in space flight.
大部份观众都知道 太空飞行是不可能加以搜救的
Any rescue system the space agency has long since calculated...
航太总署长久以来所计算的 任何搜救系统…
Any rescue system the space agency calculated...
航太总署所计算的
One sock. Once you have the sock in...
一只袜子 把袜子放好之后
we're gonna want you... Work it in.
我们要你… 放进去
...to bungee the entire filter assembly to the bulkhead...
把整个滤器用松紧带绑在隔板上
Right above the LEM canister. We're close to 15.
就在登月小艇的滤毒罐上 我们接近15了
So how does this flight compare to other emergency situations you've faced?
那这次飞行和你所见过的 其它紧急状况相比，程度有多严重？
I'll have to say that this is the most serious situation...
我得说，这是我们在 载人太空飞行中…
we've ever encountered in manned space flight.
所遭遇的最严重状况
Houston, filter's in place. Cabin gas return to egress.
休士顿，滤器装好了 座舱气体回到外出阀
Suit circuit relief to close.
关闭太空衣回路释放阀
CO2 canister select to secondary. All right.
二氧化碳滤罐订为第二选择 好
Here goes.
试试看
I can hear air moving.
我听到空气流动
Just breathe normal, fellas.
各位，维持正常呼吸
Aquarius, please advise on CO 2 status.
水瓶号，请告知二氧化碳状况
Houston, we're taking a look at those numbers now.
休士顿，我们正在看那些数字
We're still holding close to 15, Houston.
我们还是接近15，休士顿
Roger that. Standing by.
收到，稍待
Houston, the CO2 level has dropped to nine...
休士顿，二氧化碳浓度已减低至9
and it is still falling.
仍在下降中
That is good to hear, Aquarius.
水瓶号，这真是好消息
And you, sir, are a steely-eyed missile man.
长官，你真是厉害的火箭专家
Okay, spacecraft control to computer.
好，太空船交由电脑控制
Damn!
该死！
We overloaded.
我们超载了
We used way too much power.
用电过量
There must be a sneak circuit someplace between step seven and ten.
第7和第10步骤之间 一定有一个未知的电路
All right, which one has the leak?
好，哪边在漏电？
I don't know that yet, John.
我还不知道，约翰
The sequence was wrong. We just have to go back and try them one at a time.
序列不正确，我们必须回头 一个一个试
You need a break, Ken?
你要不要休息，肯？
If they don't get one, I don't get one.
他们不休息，我也不休息
Well, if it won't work, get me another one.
如果坏了，就拿另一台来
My son's supposed to be on. I know, Mrs. Lovell.
我儿子应该有上电视 我知道，勒维尔太太
Hi, Blanch.
嗨，布兰琪
They can't fix a damn thing in this place.
这里的人什么都修不好
Blanch, it's Marilyn.
布兰琪，我是玛丽莲
Hi, Grandma.
嗨，奶奶
I was gonna see Jimmy.
我本来要看吉姆的
I know.
我知道
We came to tell you something.
我们来告诉你一件事
There's been an accident. Jimmy's okay, he's all right.
发生了一件意外 吉姆没事，他很好
But he's not gonna get to walk on the moon.
但他没法登陆月球了
Well, they said he was.
可是本来说要登陆的呀
I know.
我知道
That was before.
那是以前
Now there's been an explosion, and they're all okay...
现在发生了爆炸 他们都没事
they're all right. But now they're just going to...
但他们只是需要…
try to figure out a way to get them home.
想办法回家
And it's a little bit dangerous.
有点危险
Oh, sweetie.
噢，甜心
Are you scared?
你怕了吗？
Well, don't you worry, honey.
别担心，小宝贝
If they could get a washing machine to fly...
如果他们能让洗衣机飞起来…
my Jimmy could land it.
我的吉姆就能着陆
Jack, you'll be happy to hear we contacted President Nixon...
杰克，你应该会很高兴听到 我们联络上了尼克森总统…
and he's gonna grant you an extension on your income taxes...
他答应让你延期报所得税…
since you are most decidedly out of the country.
因为你能证明你在国外
Roger that, Houston.
收到，休士顿
That's wonderful news.
真是好消息
Tell them they have to sleep.
叫他们要睡觉
Haise is running a fever of 104.
贺斯发了40度烧
13, we've got another request from the flight surgeon...
13号，医官还有一件事要吩咐
that you fellas get some more sleep.
你们必须补充睡眠
He doesn't like his readings down here.
他觉得你的生命迹象读数不佳
Let's see how he feels about this.
我们来看看他觉得这样如何
I am sick and tired of the entire western world...
整个西方世界都在看 我的肾脏功能如何
knowing how my kidneys are functioning!
我受不了了 ！
Flight, I just lost Lovell.
主任，勒维尔的读数不见了
13, this is Houston.
13号，这里是休士顿
Jim, we just had a dropout on your bio-med sensors.
吉姆，我们收不到 你的生物医疗感应
I'm not wearing my bio-med sensors, Houston.
休士顿，我把生物医疗感应器 拔掉了
Okay, Jim. Copy that.
好，吉姆，收到
Now I'm losing all three of them!
3个人都不见了 ！
It's just a little medical mutiny, Doc.
医官，这算是一点医疗叛变吧
I'm sure the guys are still with us.
我确定他们还活着
Let's cut them some slack, okay?
给他们点自由，好吧？
DAY 6
第6天
Gene, it's not the velocity, it's the angle.
金恩，不是速度问题，是角度问题
Maybe they're still venting something and that's throwing off the trajectory...
也许他们还在排气，所以 有点偏离轨道
but we are definitely shallowing again.
但我们角度又变缓了
We are up to a 5.9. Damn it.
变成5. 9 该死
At this rate, they nick the atmosphere and bounce off into space.
以这个程度来看，他们一碰到大气层 就被弹回太空去了
We need another burn to get them back.
需要再燃烧一次 他们才回得来
Another burn. Fire the engines, get on course.
再燃烧一次 点燃引擎，让他们回到轨道
Copy that.
收到
Aquarius, this is Houston.
水瓶号，这里是休士顿
Houston, Aquarius.
休士顿，水瓶号
Jim, we've got another course correction for you.
吉姆，我们要再为你修正一次航道
What's up?
怎么了？
Something about another course correction.
说要再修正一次航道
We copy, Houston.
收到，休士顿
Be advised, it's gonna take Freddo and I a while to power up the computer...
先说好，佛列德跟我要 花些时间打开电脑…
for the alignment platform if we have to fire the engine.
将平台对齐，然后才能点燃引擎
Negative on that, Jim. We can't spare power for the computer.
不行，吉姆，我们不能在电脑上 浪费动力
We gotta do this blind?
我们要蒙着眼睛做？
Houston, without the computer, what do we use for orientation?
休士顿，没有电脑怎么决定方向？
Come on, we gotta be able to give these guys something.
真是的，他们总该有什么能用的吧
Without the power, we can't give them a reading.
没有电力，就无法给他们读数
Not power. I'm talking about reference.
不是电力，我是说参考点
No, there's no references. We have a lot of debris...
没有参考点 这附近残骸太多…
Houston, what's the story with this burn?
休士顿，现在该怎么办？
We're trying to hash something out here, Aquarius.
我们在想办法，水瓶号
Stand by.
稍待
Look, Houston, all we need to hold attitude is one fixed point in space.
休士顿，我们只需要在太空中 找到一个定点来确定位置
Is that not correct? Yeah. Roger that, Jim.
是否正确？ 对，收到，吉姆
Well, Houston, we've got one.
休士顿，我们有个定点
If we can keep the Earth in the window, flying manually...
如果我们把窗外的地球位置固定 然后以手控飞行
the crosshairs right on its terminator...
把视镜中的十字线对准 地球的明暗界线
all I have to know is, how long do we need to burn the engine?
那么我只需要知道 我们必须点燃引擎多久？
The shorter, the better. Roger that, Jim.
越短越好 收到，吉姆
Can they fly it manually and still shut it down on time...
他们能不能以手控飞行 并仍然及时将引擎关闭…
without the computer?
又不用电脑？
I guess that's the best we can do. We're out of time.
现在只能这样
In order to enter the atmosphere safely...
为了安全进入大气层
the crew must aim for a corridor just two-and-a-half degrees wide.
宇航员必须对准一条 两度半宽的狭窄范围
If they're too steep, they'll incinerate in the steadily thickening air.
如果太陡，会在越来越厚的 大气中烧成灰尽
If they're too shallow, they'll ricochet off the atmosphere...
如果太缓，会被弹出大气层
like a rock skipping off a pond.
像在池中打水漂儿
The re-entry corridor is, in fact, so narrow that if this basketball were the Earth...
安全进入大气层的范围非常狭窄 假设这颗篮球是地球…
and this softball were the moon, and the two were placed 14 feet apart...
这颗垒球是月球，两者相距4公尺…
the crew would have to hit a target no thicker than this piece of paper.
宇航员必须对准的目标 就比这张纸还薄
On your toes. We're doing this one blind.
大家要注意，我们这次是 单凭仪表操作
Gene, understand that we've never tried this before:
金恩，你要知道 我们从未试过这种作法
Burn, cold soak, burn, cold soak, burn, manual control.
燃烧、 冷却、 燃烧、 冷却 燃烧、 手控
Look, it will ignite, will it not?
告诉我，引擎点得燃吧？
I just want you to know the engine's never been tried like this.
我只是要你知道 引擎从没有像这样试过
I know what you're trying to do. I guarantee I won't hold you personally responsible.
我知道你的意思 我保证绝不会要你个人负责
If it lights, it lights. Let Lovell do the rest.
如果点得燃就点得燃 剩下的让勒维尔来做
Okay.
好
They'll burn the engine and steer manually... attempting to keep the Earth in the window.
他们要点燃引擎，以手控驾驶 尽量让地球留在窗外
Okay, this is gonna take all three of us.
好，这需要我们3人合作
Freddo, you handle the pitch.
佛列德，你掌控上下角度
Put on the translation controllers, all backwards...
打开平移控制器，一直向后推
so if the Earth starts drifting down...
如果地球位置向下移…
you need to thrust aft, not forward.
就要向后打，不要向前
I'll do the same on mine with everything else.
其它也一样，都由我控制
We're going to burn at 10%% thrust for 39 seconds. Jack, you time us.
我们以10%推进力燃烧39秒 杰克，你算时间
Got it.
好
Give us a Count of the last 10 seconds up to 39. Let's not miss this.
最后10秒时请往上数到39 我们要把握机会
You up to this, Freddo?
准备好了吗，佛列德？
I'm with you.
好了
Standing by for Corridor Control burn.
准备燃烧，对准狭角
Okay, Jim, you can fire when ready.
好，吉姆，准备好了就点火
You are go for the manual burn.
你要以手控燃烧
Okay, X-Plus button at 10 seconds. Mark.
好，10秒后按钮点火
Come on, baby. One more burn. Nine, eight...
来吧，再燃烧一次 九、 八…
seven, six, five...
七、 六、 五…
four, three... Ullage is go.
四、 三… 气隙准备好了
Two, one, ignition!
二、 一，点火！
She's burning!
在烧了 ！
Master arm off. Okay, here we go.
主钮关闭 好，开始吧
Helium regulator on. RCS is go, 10% thrust.
氦气调整器开启 反应控制系统没问题，10%推动力
Bring her around, Freddo. I'm trying but it's dragging.
转过来，佛列德 我在试，可是它很慢
Ten seconds. Drop it down, Freddo.
10秒 向下压，佛列德
We're drifting! Hold What you got.
我们在漂！ 不，抓稳
I'll roll it. can't get it stable.
我来控制，退后 稳不下来
She's dancing all over the place!
船摇晃得很厉害！
Come to the right a little bit. Fifteen seconds.
向右一点 15秒
She's drifting. I'm losing attitude.
航太总署 船在漂，我失去位置了
Hold it right there. That's it. No, Freddo, back!
稳住 就这样，不行，佛列德，回来！
Shit! I'm losing it! Bring the Earth up.
妈的，失控了 ！ 让地球回到上面来
Thrust forward, Fred. Come on.
向前冲，佛列德，加油
Shit, I lost it! Where is it?
干，又不见了 ！ 在哪里？
7.'00. Helium regulator's closed.
七点钟方向，氦气调整器关闭
Bring it down, Freddo. Just nose it down.
向下移，佛列德，向下拉
Okay, I got it! Thirty seconds.
好，好了 ！ 30秒
Little farther. Ease your touch!
再过去一点，放轻一点！
Damn it, that's mine. That's me. Around.
干，是我，我的错，回来
A little more. Come on, baby. That's it. Hold it.
再多一点，加油 好，稳住
Back! That's it! Hold it! Steady. Eight, nine!
回来！ 对！ 定住！ 稳住 八、 九！
Shutdown!
熄火！
Houston, we have shutdown.
休士顿，我们熄火了
That's close enough, Jim. Good Work.
这样够近了，吉姆，干得好
I knew it! How about that LEM! How about it?
我就知道！ 这登月小艇厉害吧！ 对不对？
Guess you can keep your job. GRUMYou betcha.
你的工作大概保住了 肯定的
13, stand by. We're evaluating our power usage on that burn.
13号稍待，我们要评估刚才 燃烧的动力使用状况
Let's hope we don't have to do that again.
希望这是最后一次了
Gentlemen, you've given our guys enough to survive till re-entry.
各位，你们已给予宇航员 足够时间进入大气层
Well done.
干得漂亮
Now we gotta get them in, so tell me about the Power-up procedures.
现在我们得把他们接进来 所以告诉我供电程序
Here's the order of what I want to do.
我要做的顺序是这样
I want to power up guidance, ECS, Communications...
我要为导航、 环境控制系统 以及通讯等供电…
warm up the pyros for the ParaChutes and the Command module thrusters.
为降落伞的爆破系统 和指挥小艇推进器加热
The thrusters will Put you over budget on amPs.
推进器会让安培数超载
They've been sitting at 200 below for four days. They gotta be heated.
他们已经在摄氏负128之下过了4天 必须为他们加温
Fine. Then trade off the ParaChutes.
好吧，那就不能用降落伞了
If the Chutes don't open, what's the Point? You're telling me what you need.
如果降落伞打不开，不是白玩了？ 你告诉我你的需要
I'm telling you what we have to work with. I'm not making this stuff up.
我告诉你我们手边的资源 这可不是我瞎编的
They're going to need all these systems.
他们必须用到这所有系统
We do not have the power, Ken. We just don't have it.
我们没电了，肯 真的没有
I'll reorganize the sequencing again and find more power.
我把顺序重新编排一次 多找出一些电力
Let's start from scratch. Clear the board.
从头开始，把电盘清干净
I don't know where the hell we'll find it.
我不知道能去哪里找
Apollo 13 commander Jim Lovell has more time in space...
阿波罗13号指挥官吉姆・勒维尔 比任何其他人…
almost 24 days already, than any other man...
停留在太空中的日数都长 已经累计接近24天了
and I asked him recently if he ever was scared.
最近我访问他时 问到他是否曾感到害怕
I had an engine flame out a few times in an aircraft...
我在开飞机时曾经引擎熄火…
and was curious as to whether it was going to light up again, things of that nature...
担心它是否能再点燃，诸如此类…
but they seem to Work out.
但最后总是没事
Is there an instance in an airplane emergency when you recall fear?
你是否记得曾遭遇飞机紧急事故 而感到惧怕？
Well, I remember this one time...
我记得有一次
in a Banshee at night in combat conditions, so the carrier has no lights.
我在夜间开着死灵式战机 在战斗状况下，航空母舰没有灯
It was the Shangri-la. We were in the Sea of Japan.
是香格里拉号 我们在日本海中
My radar had jammed, and my homing signal was gone...
我的雷达受到干扰 送回的信号下落不明
because somebody in Japan was using the same frequency...
因为日本有人使用相同的频率
and so it was leading me away from where I was supposed to be.
所以让我远离了目标
I'm looking down at a big, black ocean, so I flip on my map light.
我向下望，海洋一片黑暗 所以我打开了地图灯
Then, suddenly, zap! Everything shorts out right there in my cockpit.
结果，突然吱的一声 我座舱内的所有电线都短路
All my instruments and lights are gone, I can't even tell what my altitude is.
所有仪表和指示灯都灭了 甚至看不出来我的高度多少
I know I'm running out of fuel, so I'm thinking about ditching in the ocean.
我知道我快没油了 所以我想要在海面上紧急降落
I look down there, and then in the darkness...
我向下看，然后在黑暗中…
there's this green trail.
有一条绿色的路径
It's like a long carpet that's just laid out beneath me. It was the algae!
就像在我下方铺的一条绿色地毯 那是绿藻！
It was that phosphorescent stuff that gets churned up in the wake of a big ship.
就是在大船驶过后被搅上来 会发出磷光的那种东西
It was just leading me home.
它领着我回到航空母舰
And if my cockpit lights hadn't shorted out...
如果我座舱内的灯没有短路…
there's no way I'd have ever been able to see that.
我绝对看不到它
So, you never know...
所以，你总是不知道…
What events are going to transpire to get you home.
最后会如何安然返家
Spacecraft commander Jim Lovell is no stranger to emergency.
太空船指挥官吉姆・勒维尔 见过许多大风大浪
How's it going, Fred? I'm okay.
你还好吗，佛列德？ 我没事
What the hell was that?
妈的，什么声音？
Let's hope it was just the burst disk.
最好只是氦气碟的爆破声
Can you confirm a burst helium disk? We confirm that.
是否能确认是氦气碟在爆破？ 确认
Houston, is that going to affect our entry angle at all?
休士顿，这是否影响到我们 进入大气层的角度？
Negative. Your entry angle is holding at 6.24, Aquarius.
不会，你的角度还是 6. 24度，水瓶号
Houston...
休士顿
we sure could use the re-entry procedure up here.
我们实在很需要 进入大气层的程序
When can we expect that?
预计何时能给我们？
That's coming real soon, Aquarius.
马上就来了，水瓶号
Houston, we...
休士顿，我们…
We just can't throw this together at the last minute.
我们不能等到最后一刻 才仓促准备
So, here's what you're gonna do.
所以，你们应该这样
You're gonna get the procedure up to us, whatever it is...
无论程序有多少，你们应该 传上来给我们
and we're gonna go over it step by step, so there's no foul-ups.
然后我们依照步骤练习，避免犯错
I don't have to tell you we're all a little tired up here.
我想你也知道，我们都很累了
The world's getting awfully big in the window.
从窗口看出去，地球已经很近了
Jim, this is Deke. It's Deke.
吉姆，这是迪克 是迪克
They don't know how to do it.
他们不知道该怎么做
Maybe Jack's right.
也许杰克说得不错
Hello, Deke. What's the story?
嗨，迪克，现在怎样？
We're gonna get that procedure to you as soon as we possibly can.
我们会尽快把程序给你
Ken Mattingly's in the simulator right now.
肯・马丁利现在在模拟机内
Ken's working on it?
肯在想办法？
Look, I know this sequence works, John.
我知道这个程序能用，约翰
It looks good. We're just over budget on the amperage.
看来很好，只不过我们的安培数不够
By how much? Three or four amps.
缺多少？ 3或4安培
God damn it, John! Is it three or four?
妈的，约翰！ 到底是3还是4？
Four. Four!
四 四！
Four more amps.
还要4安培
They have some power left in the LEM batteries, right?
他们登月小艇上还剩一些电力吧
Yeah.
对
We have an umbilical that provides power from the command module to the LEM.
我们有补给线从指挥小艇 提供电力给登月小艇
It's backup for the LEM power supply. I'm listening.
用来作为登月小艇的后备电源 继续说
So reverse it. Reverse the flow and see if we can draw these four amps...
把它反过来，把电流逆转 看能不能在我们丢掉登月小艇之前…
from the LEM before we cut it loose. Why can't we do that?
把这4安培的电拿回来 应该做得到吧？
We don't have a procedure for that? You'll lose a lot in the transfer.
我们没有这个程序吗？ 在传输过程中会消耗很多电力
Yeah. But all we're talking about here is four amps.
对，不过我们只需要4安培
I want whatever you guys got on these Power procedures.
你们有多少电力程序，都尽量找出来
Gene, they're already... Not all, just Part.
金恩，他们已经… 不需要全部，只要部份
We've got to give them something. They're working on it.
多少要给他们一些 他们在想办法
I'll get an estimate. God damn it!
我去找个估计值 他妈的！
I don't want another estimate! I want the procedures now!
不要再给我估计值！ 马上把程序给我！
IMU is up.
惯性测量机件打开
How am I reading? Fine, so far.
读数多少？ 目前还好
Say again. You're under limit. Keep going.
再说一次 还没超过，继续
Okay. Floodlights to fixed.
好，泛光灯全开
Okay, I'm bringing up the guidance.
好，我把导航系统打开
Here we go.
开
CMC source.
来源为指挥小艇电脑
CMC mode, auto, and we're on the computer.
指挥小艇电脑模式为自动 要开电脑了
Go ahead. Is your computer on now?
说吧 你开电脑了吗？
up and running.
电脑启动 开了
How do we look?
情况如何？
I think we got it, buddy.
我想成功了，朋友
Arthur, my notes are clear on that last sequence, right?
亚瑟，我最后一个程序的 笔迹还清晰吧？
Excuse me, gentlemen. I was getting a little blurry.
各位，借过 我这里写得有点模糊
Here's Ken. Here's John.
肯在这里，约翰在这里
It's good to see you, Ken.
很高兴见到你，肯
This is the sequence.
这是程序
Was it tried on the hardware yet? We didn't have time.
在硬体上试过吗？ 我们没时间
Aquarius, Houston. Do you read?
水瓶号，这里是休士顿，你听到吗？
Yeah, we read you, Ken.
我们听到了，肯
Are the flowers blooming in Houston?
休士顿那里开花了吗？
That's a negative, Jim. I don't have the measles.
没有，吉姆，我没得麻疹
Jim, is Jack in there with you?
吉姆，杰克在你旁边吗？
Yeah, stand by one. We gotta get him on Comm.
好，1号准备 我们叫他来听
Put those on the table. Damn it. Thanks, Jackie.
把这些放在桌上 唉呀，谢谢，杰琪
I think it would really help if you could...
如果传来坏消息时…
just distract her when the heavy Predictions come in.
你们能转移她的注意力 应该会有很大的帮助
We'll give it a shot. Thanks.
我们试试看 谢谢
Blanch, these nice, young men are gonna watch television with you.
布兰琪，这两位好心的年轻人 来陪你看电视
This is Neil Armstrong, and this is Buzz. Nice to meet you.
这是尼尔・阿姆斯特朗，这位是巴兹 幸会
Hi. Are you in the space program?
嗨 你们也参加太空计划吗？
Okay, Jack, give me a read-back on that last procedure.
好，杰克，你把最后 一个程序念给我听
Stand by, Ken.
准备好了，肯
Ken, I'm having trouble reading my own writing.
肯，我看不清楚自己的笔迹
I guess I was a little more tired than I thought.
没想到我这么累
Don't worry, Jack. I'll talk you through it.
别担心，杰克，我再说给你听
Find the main bus breakers on Panel 11.
在11号控制台上找到主配电盘断路器
Yeah, main bus breakers. Got it.
主B 主配电盘断路器，找到
Close main bus B.
关闭主配电盘B
Ken, there's an awful lot of Condensation on these Panels.
肯，这些控制板上凝结很多水气
What's the word on these things shorting out?
万一短路怎么办？
We'll just take that one at a time, Jack.
到时再说，杰克
It's like trying to drive a toaster through a Car wash.
好像把烤面包机放去洗一样危险
Main bus B is closed.
主配电盘B关闭了
13, We're coming up on entry interface.
13号，我们准备进入大气层介面了
Flight, we're still shallowing up a bit in the re-entry corridor.
大地测量位置相对于预计范围 主任，我们在返回大气层的角度上还是缓了一点
It's almost like they're underweight.
好像他们不够重一样
Now how could they be underweight? We didn't land on the moon.
怎么可能不够重？ 我们没有登陆月球啊
Rocks? That's affirm.
岩石？ 没错
One more thing. While Jack's working on the power-up, We want you and Freddo...
还有一件事，吉姆 杰克在开动电源时，你跟佛列德去…
to transfer some ballast over to the command module.
把一些压舱物转到指挥小艇去
Say again, Houston. Ballast?
什么，休士顿，压舱物？
That's affirm. We got to get the weight right.
没错，我们必须维持适当重量
We were expecting you to be toting a couple hundred pounds of moon rocks.
我们原先估计你们会带 90公斤的月球岩石回来
Right, Houston.
好，休士顿
Now, Jack. Yeah, go ahead, Ken.
现在，杰克 请说，肯
Okay, now, panel five.
现在看第5控制板
Circuit breaker caution and warning main B closed.
电路断路器警告 与预警主配电盘B关闭
Main B closed.
主配电盘B关闭
Master alarm off.
主警铃关闭
Okay, Jack, on panel seven, b-mag number two, power to warm-up.
好，杰克，在7号控制板上 2号机体高度旋转仪，打开待命
B-mag number two, power to warm-up. Done.
完成
Sequential logic one and two on.
1号和2号序号逻辑打开
Sequential logic, two on.
2号序号逻辑打开
CMRCS pressure, on.
不行 指挥小艇反应控制系统加压，打开
CMRCS Pressurization.
指挥小艇反应控制系统加压
DAY 7 As her husband prepares to jettison his lunar module lifeboat...
第7天 玛丽莲勒维尔的先生准备丢弃 他的登月小艇救生船…
Marilyn lovell waits with her children, her neighbors...
此时她和孩子与邻居一起等待…
and, we are told, Apollo 11 astronauts Neil Armstrong and Buzz Aldrin.
据说阿波罗11号的宇航员 尼尔・阿姆斯特朗和巴兹・阿尔德林也在这里
Only the Lovells' eldest son, Jay, is absent...
只有勒维尔的大儿子杰伊不在这里
as he holds vigil with his classmates...
他正在威斯康辛州的 圣约翰军校…
at the St. John's Military ACademy in wisconsin.
与同学不眠不休地注意新闻
ABC News science editor Jules Bergman.
ABC新闻纲的科学记者 朱尔斯柏格曼
With a crippled command module, and surviving by using the LEM's systems...
指挥小艇不灵 只能使用登月小艇的系统来维生
there can be no easy maneuver.
情况一定很难控制
Their LEM lifeboat is doing things and working longer...
他们的登月小艇救生船 并不是设计用来做这些工作…
than it was ever intended to.
使用这么久
It's a race against time until splashdown...
直到它坠落为止，必须争取时间
We're ready to see if the computer will accept...
我们现在准备看看电脑是否会接受…
uplink of the re-entry data now.
通讯频道所上传的 进入大气层的数据
Okay, the IMU is up.
惯性测量打开
We got our eight-balls back. copy that.
我们又看到小球了 收到
Okay, Ken, uplink telemetry, Command module to accept, right?
好，肯，上传遥测资料 让指挥小艇接受，对不对？
That's affirm. Go ahead and try it.
没错，试试看
uplink completed.
上传完成
That's more like it. Okay, let's go.
这还差不多 好，继续
Take a look at your amPs. How we doing?
看看安培数，状况如何？
We got her back up, Ken.
又回来了，肯
Boy, I wish you were here to see it.
真希望你能在这里亲眼看到
I'll bet you do.
我想也是
Way to go, Jack.
干得好，杰克
Flight, this is RETRO. Go, RETRO.
主任，这是返回地球控制员 请说
Flight, we have a typhoon warning...
主任，我们接到台风警报…
on the edge of the prime recovery zone. Say again, RETRO.
在主要坠落区边缘 再说一次，返回地球控制员
We're looking at a typhoon Warning on the edge of the prime recovery area.
我们在主要坠落区边缘接到台风警报
This is just a warning. It could miss them.
这只是警报，可能不会碰上
Only if their luck changes.
如果他们运气能转好的话
Jim, we're ready for SM jettison!
吉姆，我们准备丢弃维修小艇了 ！
All right, Jack, on three!
好，杰克，数到三！
One, two...
一、 二…
upward thrust. We're loose!
往上推进 松开了 ！
Reverse thrust!
逆向推进！
We have sevice module jettison.
美国 我们已丢弃维修小艇
Okay, Houston, servjce module is free.
好，休士顿，维修小艇已经丢弃
We'll take a look at What We have here.
我们看看接下来怎么做
Copy that.
收到
There it is. I see it!
在那里，我看到了！
Houston, we're getting our first look at the sevice module now.
休士顿，我们现在第一次看到 维修小艇了
One whole side of the spacecraft is missing.
太空船的一整边都不见了
right by the high gain antenna a whole panel is blown out...
在高增益天线旁边 一整个控制板都炸开了
right up to our heat shield.
直到我们的隔热板
Copy that, Aquarius.
收到，水瓶号
It looked like it got the engine bell, too. Can you see that?
好像连引擎钟都跟着去了 你看到了吗？
Oh, man, that's incredible.
天哪，不得了
The heat shield.
隔热板
The heat will build up to as much as 3,000 or 4,000 degrees Fahrenheit.
温度最高将逐渐达到摄氏一两千度
On a lunar re-entry flight, the heat...
从月球返航时，温度…
So, Blanch?
那，布兰琪？
Did Jim make Eagle Scout or not?
吉姆在童子军中有没有达到鹰级？
Yes, he did. He did.
有啊 他有
If the heat shield is cracked the extreme cold could've split it wide open.
如果隔热板有些微裂痕 极低的温度会把它撕裂开
Worst of all, if the pyrotechnics that control the parachutes...
最糟的是，如果控制降落伞的 爆破设备…
have been damaged, the chutes may not open at all...
受损，降落伞可能完全打不开
causing the spacecraft to hit the water not at a gentle 20 miles per hour...
使太空船不会以 时速30公里的慢速坠落，而是…
but at a suicidal 300.
每小时500公里的超高速
Perhaps never in history...
也许人类历史上…
has the entire world been united by such a global drama.
这是全世界的人头一次 一起看着这幕全球性戏剧
In NeW York City, thousands of people have gathered...
在纽约聚集了好几千人…
to watch updates of the mission in Times Square.
在时代广场观看本任务的新发展
Many countries offered help and the State Department said...
许多国家提供协助，国务院表示…
it would ask for it if it were needed.
如果需要协助，它会提出要求
The House and Senate passed resolutions calling on the people...
参众两院通过决议案，呼吁民众…
to pray tonight for the astronauts.
今晚在家为宇航员祈祷
In Rome, Pope Paul led 50,000 people...
在罗马，保罗教宗带领着5万人…
in prayers for the safe return of the astronauts.
祈求宇航员平安归来
In Jerusalem, prayers at the Wailing Wall...
在耶路撒冷，祈祷者在哭墙…
It's about time to bail out of this ship.
该弃船了
You okay?
你还好吗？
I'm freezing.
我好冷
Can you hold out just a little longer?
你能再撑一下吗？
Long as I have to. Come on.
我尽量 来
It won't be long. Just a little while longer.
不会太久的，再一下就好
Just a little while longer. We're gonna hit that water in the South Pacific.
再一下就好 我们就要进入南太平洋海中了
Open up that hatch.
打开盖子
It's 80 degrees out there. 80 degrees.
那里是摄氏30度 摄氏30度
You are a mess. Yeah.
你的情况很糟 对
Odyssey, Houston. How we doing, guys?
奥得赛，这里是休士顿 你们还好吗？
We're closing in on lunar module jettjson.
我们准备丢弃登月小艇了
As you know, that is time critical.
你知道，时间是关键因素
You should be moving into the command module.
你们应该移到指挥小艇中
Let's get that hatch buttoned up...
我们把盖子关上吧
and when you get a chance, let us know how you're doing.
有时间就告诉我们情况如何
Roger that.
收到
Let me give you a hand there, Freddo.
我来帮你，佛列德
We're coming up on LEM jettjson.
我们快丢弃登月小艇了
Is everyone strapped in, Ken? We're getting real close.
大家安全带都系好了吗，肯？ 我们快要行动了
Copy that, Flight. 13, Houston. We're coming up on LEM jettison.
收到，主任，13号，这里是休士顿 我们准备好丢弃登月小艇了
Stand by.
待命
Have you got everybody in the Odyssey?
大家都到奥得赛号上了吗？
Yeah, Ken, I'm gonna check those Pyro batteries one more time here.
对，肯，我要再检查一次 那些爆破电池
The Pyro batts look good. I don't think we have to tie the other batteries.
爆破电池看来没问题 其它电池应该不用绑起来
Sorry, Jack, this is an old habit.
抱歉，杰克，这是老习惯
I'm kind of used to the Pilot's seat. She's yours to fly.
我习惯坐驾驶位 这次让你坐
Odyssey, I want to double check some re-entry procedures...
奥得赛号，我们将在30秒后 丢弃登月小艇
right after we jettjson the LEM, Which is coming up in 30 seconds.
一丢弃后我就要再检查一些 进入大气层的程序
What is that?
这是什么？
I was getting Punchy...
我有点紧张…
and I didn't want to cut the LEM loose with you guys still in it.
怕不小心在你们还在登月小艇里时 把小艇丢弃了
That's good thinking.
想得真周到
Stand by, Houston.
准备好了，休士顿
We have lunar module jettjson.
我们已丢弃登月小艇了
She sure was a good ship.
这的确是一艘好艇
FareWell, Aquarius, and we thank you.
再见，水瓶号，我们感谢你
It's almost time, honey.
时间快到了，亲爱的
Flight 966406.
966406航班
USS IWO JIMA, SOUTH PACIFIC APRIL 17, 1970
硫磺岛号，南太平洋 1970年4月17日
Let me put it this way.
这样说吧
The traiectory may be off. Their thrusters may be frozen.
轨道可能偏差，推进器可能结冻
Their guidance system might be malfunctioning.
导航系统可能失灵
Their heat shield could be cracked.
隔热板可能破裂
And their Parachutes might be three blocks of ice.
降落伞可能变成3块冰
Clearly, we have some obstacles to overcome.
我们显然有很多阻碍
But now I'm asking you, when will we know?
但我现在问你，何时才能知道？
Blackout lasts for three minutes. If they're not back in four, we'll know.
无线电信号会受阻3分钟 如果4分钟还没有消息，就知道了
Velocity now reading 34,802 feet Per second.
速率读数是每秒10620公尺
Range to go 2,625 nautical miles. Copy that.
范围是4862公里 收到
Okay, Ken, we are aligned for re-entry. Jim, we need that computer re-entry program.
好，肯，我们已经对齐，准备进入 大气层了，吉姆，我们需要电脑程序
Fred, how are the batteries looking? Okay.
佛列德，电池状况如何？ 可以
Batt A looks good. Re-entry interface in one minute...
电池A看来不错 1分钟内进入大气层介面
Batt B, no volts, the amps are okay... and 30 seconds.
电池B无电压，安培数没问题 30秒
Batt C...
电池C…
No volts, only two amps.
无电压，只有2安培
It may die before the main chutes open.
可能会在主降落伞打开前就没电
Roger. Let's tie all the batteries onto main A and main B.
收到，我们把所有电池跟 主配电盘AB都连接
They're still shallowing a bit up there. Do you want to tell them?
他们角度还是有点缓 你要告诉他们吗？
Is there anything we can do? Not now, Flight.
还有什么能做的吗？ 现在没有了，主任
They don't need to know, do they? Copy that.
那他们就不需知道了，对不对？ 收到
RETRO says the typhoon is still a presence in the splashdown area?
返回地球控制员说 坠落区还是有台风吗？
We got the Parachute situation...
我们降落伞有状况
heat shield, angle of traiectory, and a typhoon.
隔热板有问题、 轨道角度偏差 又有台风
There are so many variables, I'm at a loss... I know what the problems are.
变数很多，我实在不… 我知道问题在哪
This could be the worst disaster NASA has experienced.
航太总署可能从未面临过 如此棘手的问题
With all due respect, sir, I believe this is going to be our finest hour.
请恕我直言 我相信这将是我们最引以为傲的一刻
Expect entry interface in 45 seconds.
预计45秒内进入介面
And on my mark, your velocity...
听到我指示后，你的速率…
will be 35,245 feet per second.
要定在每秒10742公尺
Mark 35 seconds to entry interface.
35秒钟之后进入介面
Gentlemen...
两位…
it's been a privilege flying with you.
我很荣幸与你们共事
Flight, we have loss of radio contact. Roger that.
主任，我们失去无线电联络了 收到
Expect to regain signal in three minutes.
预计3分钟之后再收到信号
It all depends on the heat shield.
一切都要靠隔热板了
Back to the lwo Jima and our live cameras there.
回到硫磺岛号和我们 那里的现场摄影机
The Navy recovery and rescue helicopters already airborne...
海军搜救直升机已经升空
cjrcling, waiting for first radar contact.
盘旋着，等待第一个雷达信号
Three minutes until drogue deployment.
3分钟之后将打开小降落伞
Standing by for any reports of acqujsitjon.
等待接收信号
One minute and 30 seconds to end of blackout.
在1分钟30秒即可再接获无线电信号
No re-entering ship has taken longer...
返回地球的太空船，总是在…
than three minutes to emerge from blackout.
3分钟之内即可恢复通讯
this is the critical moment. will the heat shield hold?
这是关键时刻，隔热板是否撑得住？
will the command module survive the intense heat of re-entry?
指挥小艇是否能抵抗 进入大气层时的高热？
If it doesn't, there'll only be sjlence.
如果无法，那我们就什么都听不到了
Mommy, you're squishing me. Sorry, sweetie.
妈咪，你挤到我了 抱歉，亲爱的
It's okay.
没关系
Okay, Flight, that's three minutes.
好，主任，3分钟了
We are standing by for acquisition. Copy that.
我们等待收取信号 收到
Odyssey, Houston. Do you read me?
奥得赛号，这是休士顿，是否听到？
Expected time of reacquisition...
预计收取信号时间…
the time When the astronauts were expected to come out of blackout...
宇航员预计结束中断期的时间…
has come and gone.
已经过去了
About all any of us can do now is just listen and hope.
我们所有人现在 只能倾听与盼望了
We're about to learn whether or not that heat shield...
我们即将知道那块…
Which was damaged by the explosion three days ago...
在3天前爆炸时损坏的隔热板…
has withstood the inferno of re-entry.
是否能抵挡得住 进入大气层时的高热
Odyssey, this is Houston. Do you read me?
奥得赛号，这是休士顿，是否听到？
Three minutes, 30 seconds. Standing by.
3分30秒，等待中
That's four minutes. Standing by.
4分钟了，等待中
Odyssey, Houston. Do you read?
奥得赛号，这是休士顿，是否听到？
Hello, Houston, this is Odyssey.
哈罗，休士顿，这是奥得赛号
It's good to see you again.
很高兴再见到你
Odyssey, Houston. Welcome home.
奥得赛号，这里是休士顿，欢迎回家
We're glad to see you.
我们很高兴见到你
Good job, Ken. Thank you.
干得好，肯 谢谢
They made it!
他们回来了 ！
Houston, we're at stable one. The ship is secure.
休士顿，我们状况稳定 太空船稳定
This is Apollo 13 signing off.
阿波罗13号通话完毕
Good job.
干得好
Our mission was called a successful failure...
我们的任务被称为 顺利的失败
in that we returned safely, but never made it to the moon.
因为我们顺利返航 但没有踏上月球
In the following months it was determined...
几个月后，据判断…
that a damaged coil built inside the oxygen tank...
是氧气槽中的一个线圈受损
sparked during our cryo stir and caused the explosion that crippied the Odyssey.
在我们低温滚动时引燃，造成爆炸 使奥得赛号无法操作
It was a minor defect that occurred two years...
这是一个小瑕疵，在2年前…
before I was even named the flight's commander.
我尚未被任命为飞行指挥官时 就发生了
Fred Haise was going back to the moon on Apollo 18...
佛列德・贺斯本来要 乘坐阿波罗18号回到月球
but his mission was cancelled due to budget cuts.
但他的任务因为预算删减而被取消
He never flew in space again.
他从此没有再回到太空
Nor did Jack Swigert, Who left the Astronaut corps...
杰克・史威格也是 他离开宇航员军团
and was elected to congress from the state of colorado.
后来当选为科罗拉多州 国会议员
But he died of cancer before he was able to take office.
但尚未就职就因癌症去世
Ken Mattingly orbited the moon as command module pilot of Apollo 16...
肯・马丁利驾驶阿波罗16号指挥小艇 环绕了月球
and flew the Space Shuttle, having never gotten the measles.
也飞过航天飞机 但从来没得到麻疹
Gene kranz retired as Director of Flight Operations just not long ago.
金恩・克兰兹不久前 才从飞行业务主任的职位退休
Many members of mission control have gone on to other things...
任务控制室中的许多成员 都另谋他职
but some are still there.
但也有人还在那里
And as for me...
至于我呢
the seven extraordinary days of Apollo 13 were my last in space.
在阿波罗13号上充满波折的7天 是我最后一次上太空
I watched other men walk on the moon and return safely...
我从任务控制室和休士顿的家中…
all from the confines of mission control and our house in Houston.
看到其他人在月球上漫步 又安全返回
I sometimes catch myself looking up at the moon...
我有时会发现自己抬头看着月亮
remembering the changes of fortune in our long voyage...
记得在我们漫长的旅程中 命运的改变
thinking of the thousands of people who worked to bring the three of us home.
想到数千人努力不懈 只希望我们3人平安回家
I look up at the moon and wonder...
我抬头看着月亮，想着…
When will we be going back...
我们什么时候再回去…
and who will that be?
到时候又会是谁呢？